<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The VVidow VVhiterows humble thanksgiving for the Kings safe return With an account of John Hall's vision upon the first day of the eleventh month, 1693/4. And also a letter to a friend concerning John Hall's message with a letter from Jamaica concerning the earthquake that happen'd there; a warning to the inhabitants of the earth, to fear God and give glory to Him, for the hour of His judgments are come Licensed, D.P. April 18.</title>
            <author>Whitrowe, Joan.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832390</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832390</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36863</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36863)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2142:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The VVidow VVhiterows humble thanksgiving for the Kings safe return With an account of John Hall's vision upon the first day of the eleventh month, 1693/4. And also a letter to a friend concerning John Hall's message with a letter from Jamaica concerning the earthquake that happen'd there; a warning to the inhabitants of the earth, to fear God and give glory to Him, for the hour of His judgments are come Licensed, D.P. April 18.</title>
                  <author>Whitrowe, Joan.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by D. Edwards in Nevel's Alley in Fetter-lane, for J.B.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cropped with faded print and some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hall, John, fl. 1694 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36863:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VVidow VVhiterows HUMBLE THANKSGIVING FOR THE KINGS SAFE RETURN. With an Account of <hi>John Hall</hi>'s <hi>Viſion</hi> upon the firſt day of the Eleventh Month, 1692/3. And alſo a Letter to a Friend concerning <hi>John Hall</hi>'s Meſſage with a Letter from <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maica</hi> concerning the <hi>Earthquake</hi> that happen'd there; a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Inhabitants of the Earth, to fear GOD and give Glory to Him, for the hour of His Judgments are come</p>
            <q>
               <p>Say unto the KING and to the Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN humble your Selves, ſit down,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Jeremiah 13.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The People of <hi>Neniveh</hi> believed GOD, and proclaimed a Faſt, and put on Sackcloth from the greateſt of them to the leaſt of them. For word came unto the King of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> and he roſe from his Throne, and he laid his Robe from him, and covered him with Sackcloth, and ſate in Aſhes.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Jonah 3.5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
               <body>
                  <p>Licenſed, <hi>D. P. April</hi> 18.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>London: <hi>Printed by</hi> D. Edwards <hi>in</hi> Nevel<hi>'s</hi> Alley <hi>in</hi> Fetter-lane, for <hi>J. B.</hi> 1694</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="thanksgiving">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36863:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Widow Whiterows</hi> HUMBLE THANKSGIVING FOR THE KING'S Safe RETURN.</head>
            <p>ONCE more I am highly honoured with Mercy and Truth to return Thanks to the Moſt High for the Kings ſafe Return.</p>
            <p>Oh what ſhall I ſay to the LORD for all his Mercies and boundleſs Favours, for I am as one aſtoniſh'd at his Goodneſs; How wonderful are his Works and his Ways paſt finding out; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore who ſhall not admire Thee: Thou King of Righteouſneſs, who hath all Power in Heaven and Earth in thy Hands, to bind the Kings of the Earth in Chains, and their Nobles with fetters of Iron, who ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt in the Heavens, and makes bare the Arm of thy Glorious Power in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36863:3"/>the Earth to daſh the Nations aſunder, and break in pieces the Potſherds of the Earth as a Potter's Veſſel.</p>
            <p>Oh Great LORD, glorious in Power, fearful in Praiſes, doing won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Thou LORD <hi>Jehovah</hi> art come, and thy Power goes before Thee, that ſhall rend the Rocks, and cleave the Mountains in ſunder: The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting GOD is come to throw down Mountains and Hills, and to exalt the low Valleys; he'll awaken the Earth by his thundring Power, and the ſleepy Inhabitant thereof by his loud ſounding Judgments: For this know, Oh King:
<q>
                  <l>There's neither Strength nor Policy ſhall ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Againſt what GOD's a bringing on this Land.</l>
                  <l>The Youth ſhall howl, the Aged ſhall weep ſore,</l>
                  <l>Yet there's glad tidings for the Meek and Poor.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Poor in Spirit, I mean, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.3. who are Heirs of the Kingdom of Glory, whom GOD will hide in the hollow of his Hand whilſt his fierce Indignation paſſes over the Rebellious; wherefore, Oh that my Counſel might be acceptable to the King, and that his ways might ſo pleaſe the LORD, as that his days may be prolonged in this Land, which the LORD for a time hath given him to do the will of GOD in all things with all his Might, and with all his Strength, that theſe heavy Judgments which the LORD hath pronounced may not be executed in the King's days; For thus ſaid the LORD to me in my deep humiliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Controverſie is not with Man or Woman farther than they are found in the Tranſgreſſion, take away the Tranſgreſſion; and where's my Controverſie.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo, O Righteous LORD, that thy Controverſie is not with Man or VVoman farther than they are found in the tranſgreſſion of thy Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law, and pure Commandments? Oh then for thy Mercy ſake, and the advancement of thy Glorious Power, and the praiſe of thy ever Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Name in theſe Nations, and throughout all the Earth, turn the King and Queens Hearts with all their Powers and Strengths to Thee, as the Rive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of VVaters are turned, that with a powerful force of Thy Love and ardent Affection to thy Glory, they may joyn unanimouſly together in Heart and Soul to humble themſelves in the duſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Thee the Almighty GOD, repenting with <hi>Niniveh</hi>'s Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.7, 8. For no leſs Repentance will put a ſtop to the hot and fiery Indignation of the LORD which is kindled againſt this Land, but to turn every one from his Evil Way, and from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36863:3"/>wickedneſs that is in their hands; therefore, Oh noble Prince an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Princeſs, for the LORD's ſake, who is the King of Eternal Glory, the GOD of the Spirits of all Fleſh, the Everlaſting Counſellor, the Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Peace, the GOD that made the Heavens and Earth, the Sea, and all tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therein is, who hath delivered the King from all his Enemies, and gav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him his Life for a Prey, and for the LORD JESUS CHRIST's ſake, his Suf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fering, Life, and Bloody Paſſion, who was nail'd to the Croſs, and gave u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Life there for all Mankind, and roſe again for the Salvation and Redemption of the Faithful. I pray again and again for His ſake wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath been with the King in ſix troubles, and in the ſeventh by his out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtretch'd Arm hath deliver'd him: Oh for His ſake come down from your Thrones, and humble your ſelves in the duſt by Faſtings and Prayers, and deep Humiliation, crying mightily to GOD the Father of all your Mercies that He would be with you in Counſel, and direct your way in truth before Him, to do His moſt acceptable will in all things, that in his infinite compaſſions for his great and terrible name ſake ſhew you what to do, and which way to take for the ſuppreſſing, and total deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this boundleſs flood of Ungodlineſs that overflows theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>And deareſt Prince and Princeſs, I humbly beg and beſeech you for the LORD, and his Glory ſake, and for your own Lives and Liberty ſake be not negligent in this great VVork, proſtrating your ſelves night and day before the Throne of his Grace, crying mightily to him for his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Power, Heavenly VViſdom, and Holy Zeal; which his Valiants had of Old. <hi>Phinehas, Numbers</hi> 25, 7, 8, 11. <hi>Jehoſhaphat, Hezakiah,</hi> and <hi>Joſias,</hi> theſe were clad with Zeal as with a Garment, theſe were the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liants of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that knew how to handle weapons of VVar being girt with the Sword of the Spirit, and Helmet of Salvation. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nehas</hi> was honourable, who by his holy Zeal ſtop'd the Plague from the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> then ſaid the LORD unto <hi>Moſes, Phinehas the Son of</hi> Eleazar <hi>hath turned mine Anger away from the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>while he was zealous for my ſake among them, therefore I have not conſumed the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in my Jclouſie, wherefore ſay unto him, Behold I give unto him my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Peace, and he ſhall have it, and his Seed after him for Ever, becauſe he was zealous for his God, and hath made him an attonement for the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael. Oh what an influence had this upon the LORD, and how this act of Holy Zeal pleas'd his Divine Majeſty; here we may ſee the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between a holy Zeal for GOD and his Glory, and a blind Zeal that hath any Intereſt in it to Self-honour, either in Name, or Fame, or any other thing of this periſhing VVorld: The firſt hath power to prevail with GOD, to ſtop the Judgment; the latter ſuffers it to go on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36863:4"/>to their own deſtruction: But wo and alaſs, where are theſe holy Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ots now in our age, that lies proſtrating themſelves before the LORD <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight and day? And though they ſee the Sword of the LORD drawn over theſe Nations; as <hi>David</hi> and the Elders of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.16, 17. which were cloathed in Sackcloth, falling upon their Faces, crying out moſt bitterly before the LORD with rended hearts, ſaying, <hi>Is it not I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat have ſinned, and have committed Evil in thy Sight?</hi> Is it not I That have loved Covetouſneſs, which is Idolatry? Is it not I that have gone a whoring from thee after my Luſts and Pleaſures, my Silver and Gold, Pride and Profits of a periſhing World, ſo long till I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked the Eyes of thy Glory to ſay as thou didſt to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, <hi>For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hree Tranſgreſſions, and for four, I will not paſs by the Iniquities thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Oh LORD GOD let thy hand be upon me, and my Fathers Houſe, to bring me to a true and unfeigned Repentance, offering unto Thee Body, Soul, and Spirit a Sacrifice of Righteouſneſs, to love and ſerve Thee all the days of my appointed time, until my Change com: And thus in judging and condemning your ſelves, and bearing the Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the LORD, the Altar is ſet up in the Threſhing-Floor of <hi>Orman</hi> the <hi>Jebuſite,</hi> where true Penitents ſacrifice their Luſts, vile Affections, and their own wills, ways, and works; this is the Valley of <hi>Jehoſha— <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat,</hi> where <hi>Mohab</hi> ſhall be threſhed to pieces, <hi>Iſa</hi> 5.10. as Straw is thraſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Madmenah;</hi> therefore ſaith GOD, <hi>Let the Heathen be awakened, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome up to the Valley of</hi> Jehoſhaphat <hi>for there will I ſit to Judge all the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen round about.</hi> Therefore Oh Multitude, Multitude, come into the Valley of Threſhing, for the day of the LORD is near in the valley of Threſhing; here will God plead with all Fleſh, here will he Judge between the Precious and the Vile, and when you have born the indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the LORD for Sin and Iniquity ſo long till Judgment turns to Victory, then will he ariſe and plead your Cauſe: The word <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> ſignifies Pleading, or Judgment, and that which is call'd the valley of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> was before called the valley of, <hi>Berachah,</hi> (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.26.) which ſignifies Bleſſing or Thankſgiving; and from hence proceeds the true and acceptable Praiſe from the valley of Judgment, where GOD de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the Iniquity, and ſo it comes to paſs that whatſoever is done in the Hiſtory muſt be done again in the Myſtery; therefore, whoſoever will have Life and Salvation muſt come into the Valley of Judgment. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udge your ſelves, hate and abhor your ſelves, believe your ſelves from the bottom of your Souls to be the vileſt, and unworthieſt of all the Creatures of GOD, in reſpect to your diſobedience, and rebellion againſt Him and his Holy Laws, and this muſt be your Work in the beſt ſtate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36863:4"/>you have yet attained to, yea, if you were come to ſuch a Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>Paul</hi> was come to when he ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Though I know no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing by my ſelf, yet herein am I not juſtified; but he that juſtifies me is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> LORD.</hi> Therefore how much more ought it to be the daily and hourl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> work of thoſe that call themſelves Chriſtians of this Generation, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are ſo loaded with Sin, that the Spirit of God, both within and withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them is oppreſſed, as a Cart is oppreſſed under the Sheaves; but leſt any ſhould think I mean a bare Hiſtorical Judging, or Pharaſaical crying out <hi>LORD have Mercy upon us miſerable Sinners:</hi> Here you may cry out long and loud as <hi>Jezebels</hi> Prophets did, and never be heard or anſwered; no no, I mean a going down into the valley of Judgment; the valley of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat</hi> where God himſelf will ſit to Judge the Heathen, that knows not him nor his Righteous Judgments, and yet are crying out, <hi>LORD have Mercy upon them miſerable Sinners,</hi> who never knew this River of <hi>Jordan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.14. or Judgment to cleanſe them of their Leproſie, their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down into the deep, where they behold his Wonders, this valley of Tears, where <hi>Luke</hi> 10.39. <hi>Mary</hi> ſate to hear the precious words that came from his gracious Lips, which are not to be heard but by leaving all the hurryings, and turmoiling Incumbrances of a periſhing World to ſit attentively at his Feet; ſeeking, loving, admiring nothing but Him, no, not its own life but for his ſake, that it may ſerve him therewith; and this was the pleaſure and treaſure of all the regenerated Chriſtians that were born again both under the Law and Goſpel; and this way in which they attain'd this Reſurrection, and holy life, was through Judgment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will</hi> (ſaith David) <hi>ſing of Mercy and Judgment to thee Oh my Strength, will I ſing. Bleſſed are they that keep Judgment, and do Righteouſneſs at all times, I will praiſe thee with an upright heart. When I have learned thy Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, my Fleſh trembleth for fear of Thee, and I am afraid of Thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The Fear of the LORD is clean,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and endures for ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The Judgments of the LORD are Truth and Righteous altogether, more to be deſired than Gold, yea, than much fine Gold, ſweeter than the Honey, and the Honey-Comb: Moreover by them is thy Servant warned, or made Circumſpect, and in keeping of them there is great Reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.13. the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and the <hi>Thummim,</hi> which ſignifies light and perfection, or Knowledge and Holineſs: GOD commanded i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be put into the Breaſt-plate of Judgment, which was to be upon <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Heart continually when he went in before the LORD.</p>
            <p>And now Chriſt our Pattern, and High-Prieſt for ever after the Order of <hi>Melchiſadeck,</hi> fulfilled that Heavenly Inſtitution in his Earthly Body who bore the Judgment of GOD upon his Heart in his ſuffering life
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36863:5"/>which he hath in his merciful loving Kindneſs, as it were, left us a lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y or Portion to be like unto him in all things, to fill up that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ehind of his Sufferings in our Fleſh; for it is not only given us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieve, but to ſuffer for his ſake; but I would not have you miſtaken; I do not confine all true Chriſtians to thoſe external Sufferings of Chriſt, as Mockings, Scourgings, and nailing to the Croſs, for it may be, ſome may not be called to ſuffer on that wiſe, but the Sufferings I now treat of, are the Internal ſufferings of the Soul, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of when he ſaid, <hi>I bear in my Body the Dyings of the LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and ſaid our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>If ye ſuffer with me, ye ſhall Reign with me;</hi> mark that, with Him: That is a Heart-breaking Suffering, an inward Suffering, to be grieved in the very bottom of your Souls if you do the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſt thing that grieves the Spirit of GOD in you, keeping ſo intent to your Watch, that you may ſee the Tempter before he comes, and then your Weapons are to be the Sword of GODs Spirit, your Prayers and Supplications, with ſtrong Cries, even as a Woman in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ail, to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her of Power to give you his Heavenly Strength, ſo to make War with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Enemy of your Souls as to overcome all his temptations, to fight manfully, and couragiouſly with your ſelves, with your own deſires, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, ſelf-love, any corrupted Reaſon, and your own Wills: Theſe are the potent Enemies of Chriſt, that keeps him from his Right to Reign in your Souls; here you are to help the LORD againſt the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, which is Sin, Fleſh, and the Devil, which you are to engage War withal, old <hi>Adam,</hi> the Dragon, and <hi>Lucifer,</hi> which you are to adventure your Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates to overcome; and they that looſes their lives here ſhall find them; and they that holds out to the End here ſhall be Saved; and they that forſakes theſe ſhall receive a thouſand fold, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth in this Life, and that which is to come. Theſe are the ſufferings you are to join with Chriſt in; here you muſt be equal workers together with him, mark that, not without him, for without him we can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, poor miſerable nothings, from the Greateſt to the Leaſt; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f we wait upon him in the contempt of our ſelves, in ſelf-abhorrence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oor Impotent Creatures, waiting at the Pool of <hi>Betheſda, John</hi> 5.45. 6, 7, 8. for the Angels, moving the Waters; here's the place where Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us comes with his Mercy, and healing Power, and Vertue, which makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lame leap as an Hart, the Blind to ſee, the Deaf to hear, the Dumb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſpeak, the Dead to live, and heals all your putrified Sores; but have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> care your Eve is not to Man for help, you muſt not ſeek to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures, for that was <hi>Aſa</hi> King of <hi>Juda</hi>'s Sin, who reſted on the King of <hi>Aram,</hi> and not on the LORD; therefore, ſaid the Prophet <hi>Hanani</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36863:5"/>to King <hi>Aſa, The Hoſt of</hi> Aram <hi>is eſcaped out of thy Hand,</hi> and when he was afflicted with an extream Diſeaſe in his Feet, he ſought to the Phyſicians, and not to the LORD, and ſo died, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. and not to the LORD to take away the Sin, which was the cauſe of God's afflicting hand upon him; yet, a King that did many noble acts to pull down Idolatry, and made a Covenant to ſeek the LORD with his whole Heart and Soul, and made a Law, that whoſoever would not ſeek the LORD GOD of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhould be Slain, whether ſmall or great, Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, yet in this thing he greatly tranſgreſſed himſelf. See what a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous thing it is to rely upon Man for help, either for Soul or Body, either in ſpiritual or temporal Affairs, 'tis no leſs than a diſ regarding the LORD, and believing his Omnipotency to be inſufficient, and how this can be anſwered, let the wiſe in Heart judge; but the remedy for this raging, peſtilential Diſeaſe, is the foregoing Inſtructions, to be empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of our ſelves, to be made nothing, to forſake our own Wills; theſe are Sufferings indeed, all other outward Sufferings, of what ſort ſoever, are but ſhadows to theſe; though you give up your Bodies to be burnt, that doth but reach the Fleſh, but theſe reach the Soul, thoſe takes away the Life, but theſe the Sin, for example; How many hundreds, or thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands ſuffers outwardly variety of ways, as Poverty, Sickneſs, and Death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as wicked as ever, but the internal Sufferings reaches the Heart, and changes it from evil to good: Therefore theſe are the Sufferings that brings Chriſt to reign in the Soul here, whilſt it is in the Body, in the Life, and then hereafter for ever; wherefore here we are to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Chriſt our Pattern in his Suffering Life. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. <hi>Let this Mind be in you,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>which was in Chriſt Jeſus. who being in the form of GOD, thought it no Robbery to be equal with GOD, yet made himſelf of no Reputation, and took upon him the form of a Servant, and was made in the likeneſs of Men, and being found in faſhion as a Man, he humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto Death, even the death of the Croſs:</hi> Here's our Pattern, he that was LORD of all, became leaſt of all, although he was GOD, equal with the Father, yet he emptied himſelf of all his Glory, and humbled himſelf to an Ignominious Death; which ſignifies a death to all your Honours and Glories, you muſt empty your ſelves, not only of all Sin and Iniquity, as Pride, Arrogancy, Deceit, Malice, Hatred, Covetouſneſs, and the like; but of all your beſt Endowments, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of Graces, Parts, and Wiſdom, your good Works, that are really good in themſelves, works of Mercy to your Neighbours, and fellow-Creatures; or whatſoever Excellency doth atttend a Heavenly Life, that thou thinkeſt thou oughteſt to think well of it, or thy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36863:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36863:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36863:7"/>ſelf for doing it; away with thoſe Thoughts, hate and abhor ſuch Thoughts, thou oughteſt to run away from them Thoughts, as Chriſt did from the <hi>Jews</hi> when they would have made Him King: For what haſt thou done that was not commanded thee, therefore the good that thou doſt is none of thine; thou haſt nothing, thou art nothing, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is thine, but Sin; thou never didſt a good action, nor never thought a good thought; ſhall I therefore aſcribe to my ſelf the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of doing any good, to rob GOD of his Honour, GOD forbid, all good is GOD's, but Sin, Evil, and Wickedneſs is thine; therefore down proud Worm, down Duſt and Aſhes, down with your Crowns before the Lamb, and Him that ſits upon the Throne, and confeſs and aſcribe in the deepeſt humility, and profoundeſt adoration from the bottom of your Souls; all Praiſe, Power, Might, and Dominion, Honour and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the LORD GOD Omnipotent, from Everlaſting to Everlaſting. Amen. Wherefore, if you will find GOD, it muſt be by leſning your ſelves, making ſelf of no Reputation; by emptying your ſelves of all your Glories and Excellencies, whether external or internal, and take nothing to your ſelves but ſhame and confuſion of Face, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. and that in a broken and contrite Heart, judging and condemning your ſelves to be unworthy of the leaſt of all his Goodneſs, and this is the Breaſt-plate of Judgment, that muſt be upon <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Heart continually before the LORD; then you learn of Chriſt, who emptied and humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in all things to be tempted as we are, yet without Sin, and thus Man comes to be reſtored to GOD out of the Fall; for, as in <hi>Adam</hi> all died, ſo in Chriſt all are made alive to Righteouſneſs and true Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: If we put him on, as tis written, <hi>Put ye on the LORD Jeſus, and make no proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfil the Luſt thereof:</hi> This is that that recovers Mankind out of the Fall, to put on His Righteouſneſs, His Humility, to put on His Obedience to the Father, His Self-denial, His Juſtice, His Mercy, and to be cloathed with all His Heavenly Vertues: This is better than an adherent, or an imputed Righteouſneſs, which without this we are never the better for, but here we eat His Fleſh, and drink His Blood, that nouriſhes and gives life to our Souls, and cauſes us to grow from Grace to Grace, till we come to the perfect ſtature of the fulneſs of GOD in Chriſt, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 4.13.14, 15. <hi>That we henceforth be no more Children, toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of Doctrine, by the ſlight of Men, and cunning craftineſs whereby they lye in wait to deceive. But ſpeaking the Truth in Love, may grow up into him in all things which is the Head; even Chriſt.</hi> Oh Praiſes to GOD for ever, for this means, this is the means, if you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36863:7"/>make uſe thereof, that ſhall make you wiſe unto Salvation, not the wiſdom of this World, nor the Princes thereof, that comes to nought which is humane and diabolical, the wiſdom of the Serpent, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Tree, of which GOD ſaid, <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die;</hi> die to the life of Innocency, but live to Man's own Will, Wiſdom, and Skill, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calls Death it ſelf, and the Apoſtle, <hi>James</hi> 3.15.13. calls it Earthly, humane, and deviliſh Wiſdom, and it may well be called ſo, for it doth the Devils work, it lifts Men up above all that is called GOD, to admire themſelves, to kiſs their own hand, Idolizing their own Gifts, Wiſdom, and Parts, Reaſon, Honeſty, Knowledge and Art. And where's the Man that adores not himſelf here? And can there be greater Idolatry than this, for a Man to pride himſelf, Phariſee-like, in his own attainments? This was <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi>'s Sin, which provoked the Higheſt to throw him to the Beaſts of the Field, <hi>Dan</hi> 4.20 28, 29. till he knew that the Moſt High rul'd in the Kingdoms of Men; and this is the crying Sin of Mankind, now to think well of themſelves, their own Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs, and to follow their own wills, conceits, and opinion of good; which indeed is falſe, as to know much, learn much, to diſcern many Sciences, and in ſome to aim to become Gods, as might be ſpoke more fully to, had I time; yet at the ſame time, all their humane Wiſdom and Knowledge doth not ſhew them that this was <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall, the biting of the Apple, and his bitter death: Therefore, ſaid GOD, I think, to <hi>Tyrus. Thy Wiſdom hath blinded thine Eyes.</hi> Therefore, Oh Man, that wherein thou judgeſt <hi>Adam,</hi> thou condemneſt thy ſelf; thou art the Man that eats of this forbidden Tree, while thou art following thy own Will and Wiſdom, which is the head of the Serpent, that muſt be bruiſed by the Power of Chriſt before thou canſt come to that Eſtate which Chriſt ſpake of, by which we muſt enter. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.3. the Kingdom of GOD; to wit, <hi>As a little Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh my GOD, Is this the ſtation we muſt all come to, to be Converted, and become <hi>as a little Child,</hi> before we can enter thy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Kingdom of Everlaſting Joy, Peace, and Reſt? Then, how far LORD, muſt the Wiſe and Prudent of this World travel back to undo all that ever they have done by the Serpents cunning Wit, and ſenſual Wiſdom? To be ſtript of all their Glories in natural Parts Gifts, and Arts, both of Fleſh and Spirit, To ſtand as naked in themſelves before Thee, the pure God, as <hi>Adam,</hi> when he tranſgreſſed, before they can be cloathed with thy Innocency and Humility; for if we conſider the ſtate of a young Infant, it knows nothing but to lye at the Breaſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36863:8"/>and ſuck the Milk that nouriſhes and cauſes it to grow, it hath no cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning contrivance of will or wit to preſerve it ſelf from danger, you may do what you will with it, it cannot help it ſelf: but if any thing ails it that it ſuffers, it cries for the Breaſt: Juſt ſo it is with the Regenerated Man, the New-born Man, that Chriſt our Saviour ſpake to <hi>Nicodemus</hi> of: But did this wiſe Man, tho' a Ruler in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> underſtand what Chriſt meant? No; no more than the Teachers and Rulers of this Generation. But, as Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> ſaid, <hi>As Parrots by rote:</hi> Nor would theſe give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the trouble of that, but for their Self-Intereſt in one kind or other; ſome for yearly maintenance, others for Name and Fame, or to be highly eſteem'd of for their Gifts and Parts; therefore all of this ſort comes ſhort of the Life of Inocency; therefore what can be expected when the Prieſts and Rulers of Nations or Kingdoms are ſo corrupted with By-ends and Self-reſpects, But that the People ſhould be infected with the ſame peſtilential Diſeaſe of Poyſon and Sedition, both againſt God and Man; and corrupted with all manner of groſs Impieties, both publick and private Sins, which calls aloud for Vengeance, when the Iniquity thereof is fully ripe.</p>
            <p>But to the aforeſaid <hi>Rabbies, Doctors,</hi> and great <hi>Scholars;</hi> theſe were the Men that crucified Chriſt in the Days of his Fleſh; and are not theſe the Men in our days that crucify the Lord of Life afreſh, and puts him to an open ſhame by their wicked and impious Lives, by which the whole World is fill'd with Atheiſtical Spirits, that denies God and Chriſt? Are not theſe the Anti-chriſts, that preaches Chriſt in words, but in works denies both the Father and the Son, yet theſe are the Men that carries the World before them, that pretends to know all things as to reſolve any point in Divinity, and give the Interpretation of any place of Scripture; and ſo fill the World with their Expoſitions; But what fruit to God hath all this Bluſtring brought forth? <hi>For the Tree is known by its Fruit,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: Have they ſet up their Lights, that the VVorld may ſee their Holy and Righteous Lives? Are their Converſations in Heaven, and ſo transformed and made new Creatures? Do they live the inward and ſpiritual Life of the VVord they preach? Are they dead to the VVorld, and the VVorld to them? Doth the Life of Chriſt ſhine in them, and by them, ſo that they live no longer to themſelves, but to Chriſt; and ſo fetch'd off their own Bottoms, that they are ingrafted into Chriſt the LORD of Life and Glory?</p>
            <p>But wo and alas, is it not quite contrary to all this? Are not theſe the Men that follows the World moſt, wallowing in the Pleaſures, Profits, Honours, and Humour thereof, having Mens Perſons in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36863:8"/>becauſe of their advantage, ſeeking, greeting in publick Places, cauſing Men to fall upon their Knees, adoring them as Gods, and loving the uppermoſt Seats at Feaſts, making long Prayers to get the praiſe of Men, being mightily deſirous of Vain-glory, and the Wealth of the World, but if theſe fail, they are dead and heartleſs; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all theſe things diſcovers where they are below in the World, and not above with GOD; but if you be the true Miniſters of Chriſt, and Chriſtians indeed, ſhew your Humility and Self-denial; let the life of Chriſt appear in the fruits thereof; for you know Chriſt in all his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine calls for fruits, and what he called upon others, for he ſhewed forth himſelf in Life and Practice: For, ſaid he, <hi>A good Tree cannot bring forth evil-Fruit;</hi> and you know, the Tree that did not bring forth Fruit was Curs'd. Therefore, the true Miniſters of Chriſt trod in the ſteps of their LORD; they lived in the offering up of their Souls con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in the flames of Love, as a whole Burnt-offering to Chriſt, which is the practical part, and kept their Bodies under, that while they were Preachers to others, they might not be caſt aways themſelves, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.26. they went on conquering, and to conquer, and ſo doth every true Chriſtian; they are ſtill conquering, and overcoming all their Enemies, getting their Sins and Luſts under their Feet, and can never reſt whilſt there is any to overcome, till they have brought all in Subjection, and this they are able to do, through the Power of Chriſt in them; although the falſe Prophets, and Miniſters of Antichriſt, who are Miniſters of the Fleſh, and not of the Spirit, that tells them to the contrary, for their ſiniſter ends, to keep up their Trade of <hi>Diana. Acts</hi> 19.24. But alas, who do I give this aforeſaid Doctrine to? For it muſt be a <hi>Caleb</hi> that muſt do this work, a <hi>Caleb,</hi> which ſignifies a good Heart, not a Heart that ſeeks Liberty to the fleſh, to make the knowledge of Chriſt a more eaſie way to ſinning, to encourage them in their Luxury, and Fleſhly Pleaſures, not an Heart of unbelief, that brings an evil report upon the good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and, to make the death of Chriſt of no effect, ſaying, We ſhall never overcome our Sins and Luſts, being ſo many, potent, and ſtrong, while we are on this ſide the Grave. No, no, this is not the Heart that ſhall overcome but a couragious, valiant heart, that's fill'd with Faith and Love, that ſtands armed upon its Watch-Tower againſt every high and wandring thought, ſtrong hold, and vain Imagination, that exalts it ſelf againſt the Power, Kingdom, and Soveraignty of Chriſt, that ſo it may kill Sin in the Conception, before it be brought to the Birth; and this is the way that Chriſt and his Apoſtles aſcribed to work out your Salvation with Fear and Trembling, that we be equal
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36863:9"/>workers together with him, and then Co-heirs, for he places our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conditionally, if we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo Reign with him, ſo then this ſuffering life is the door all muſt come in at; for, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>He that comes another way is a Thief, and a Robber;</hi> ſo here's no Salvation, but by being partakers of his Internal. Sufferings, which <hi>Hermes Triſmigeſtes</hi> doth excellently treat of in his firſt Book. For this only, Oh Son, ſaith he, is the way to the Truth, which our Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors travelled in, and by which making their Journey, they at length at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the good; it is a venerable way and plain, but hard and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult for the Soul to go in, that is, in the Body: For firſt muſt it war againſt its own ſelf, and after much ſtrife and diſſention, it muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome of one part, for the contention is of one againſt two, whilſt it flies away, and they ſtrive to hold and detain it; but the Victory of both is not like, for the one haſteth to that which is good, but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a Neighbour to the things that are Evil, and that which is good deſireth to be ſet at Liberty, but the things that are evil love Bondage and Slavery: And if the two parts be overcome, they become quiet and are content to accept of it as their Ruler; but if the one be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the two, it is by them led and carried to be puniſh'd by its Being and continuance here. This is Oh Son, the guide in the way that leads thither; for thou muſt firſt forſake the Body before thy End, and get the Victory in this contention, and ſtrifeful Life, and when thou haſt overcome, then return, and avoid all converſation with the Multitude, or common People, for I would not have thee ſubject to Envy, for they do rather ſharpen and whet evil Men to their Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, therefore it behoveth to avoid the Multitude, and take heed of them, as not undeſtanding the Virtue and Power of the things that are ſaid: And in the ſecond Book, where he began to Preach unto Men the Beauty and fairneſs of Piety and Knowledge; ſaying, Oh ye People, Men born and made of the Earth, which have given your ſelves over to drunkenneſs, and ſleep, and to the ignorance of GOD. Be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ceaſe your ſurfeit, whereto you are allured and invited by bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, and unreaſonable ſleep: Why, Oh Men of the off-ſpring of the Earth, why have you delivered your ſelves over unto death, having power to partake of Immortality; repent and change your Minds you that have together walked in Error, and have been darkned in Ignorance, depart from that dark Light, be partakers of Immortality, and leave, or forſake Corruption.</p>
            <p>And ſome of them that heard me, ſaid he, Mocking, and Scorning, went away, and delivered themſelves up to the way of Death.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:36863:9"/>
            <p>But others caſting themſelves down before my Feet, ſaid he, Beſought me, that they might be taught, but I cauſed them to riſe up, I became a guide to Mankind, teaching them the reaſons how, and by what means they may be ſaved, and I ſowed in them the words of Wiſdom, and nouriſhed them with <hi>Ambroſian</hi> water of Immortality. I ſhall ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his great Viſion, which in order ſhould have gone firſt; How God appeared to him, calling him by his Name, ſaying, What wouldſt thou hear and ſee, or what wouldſt thou underſtand to learn and know: Then ſaid <hi>Hermes,</hi> Who art thou? I am quoth he, <hi>Poemanders,</hi> the Mind of the Great LORD, the moſt Mighty and abſolute Emperour, I know what thou wouldſt have, and I am always preſent with thee. Then ſaid I, I would learn the things that are, and underſtand the nature of them, and know GOD. How, ſaid <hi>Poemander,</hi> know God? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that I would gladly hear. Then, ſaid he, have me again in thy Mind, and whatſoever thou wouldeſt learn, I will teach it thee.</p>
            <p>When he had thus ſaid, he was changed, his Idea or Form, and ſtraightway in the twinkling of an Eye, all things were opened unto me, and I ſaw an infinite ſight, all things were become light, both ſweet and exceedingly pleaſant, and I was wonderfully delighted in the beholding it: But after this, there was a darkneſs fearful and hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, inſomuch that <hi>Hermes</hi> trembled at his Idea, or Form, which I cannot now inſiſt further upon: How GOD revealed himſelf to him, making known the myſtery of his outward and inward Creation, which is wonderful and excellent, and is committed to Poſterity, though in an obſcure, or hidden Stile.</p>
            <p>But having not room here for the Viſion, being much, I ſhall only touch at ſomething as I go along, that may be ſerviceable to my matter in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poemander:</hi> GOD ſaid, Let the Man endued with a Mind, mark, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and know himſelf well: <hi>Hermes;</hi> Have not all Men a Mind <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander?</hi> Take heed what thou ſayeſt: I the Mind come unto Men that are holy, and good, pure, and merciful, and live piouſly, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and my Preſence is a help to them, and forthwith they know all things, and lovingly they ſupplicate and propitiate the Father, and bleſſing him, they give him thanks, and ſing Hymns unto him, being ordered, and directed by filial affection, and natural love, and before they give up their Bodies to the Death of them, they hate their Senſes, knowing their Works and Operations.</p>
            <p>Or rather, I that am the Mind it ſelf, will not ſuffer the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Works, being the Porter and Door-keeper. I will ſhut up
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36863:10"/>the entrances of Evil, and cut off the Thoughtful Deſires of filthy Works.</p>
            <p>But to the fooliſh, and evil, wicked, envious, and covetous, murderous, prophane. I am far off giving place to the revenging Demon, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying unto him the Sharpneſs of Fire tormenteth ſuch a Man ſenſible, and armeth him the more to all wickedneſs, that he may obtain the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Puniſhment: and ſuch a one never ceaſeth having unfulfillable Deſires, and unſatiable Concupiſcences, and always fighting in Darkneſs. For the Demon afflicts, and tormenteth him continually, and increaſeth the Fire upon him more and more. For the Soul entring into the Body of Men if it continue evil, ſhall neither taſte of Immortality, nor is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the Good.</p>
            <p>But the Soul of Man which is pious and religious is Angellical and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; and ſuch a Soul after it is departed from the Body, having ſtriven the ſtrife of Piety, becomes either mind or divine; and the ſtrife of Piety is to know <hi>GOD,</hi> and to injure no Man, and this way it becomes Mind. But into a pious Soul the Mind entring, leads it into the Light of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: and ſuch a Soul is never ſatisfied with ſinging Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe to <hi>GOD,</hi> and doing good to all Men, both in VVords and Deeds; always doing good in imitation of her Father. And this Mind in Men is <hi>GOD;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are ſome Men <hi>Divine,</hi> and their Humanity is near <hi>Divinity.</hi> For the good <hi>Demon</hi> called the <hi>Gods</hi> Immortal Men, and Men Mortal Gods.</p>
            <p>Man had more than all living Creatures, and the World, becauſe of his Speech and Mind; alſo Man became the Spectator of the Works of GOD, and wondred, and acknowledged the Maker; for he divided Speech among all Men, but not Mind, and yet he envied not any, for Envy comes not thither, but is of abode here below in the Souls of Men that have not the Mind.</p>
            <p>But wherefore, Father, did not GOD diſtribute the Mind to all Men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hermes.</hi> Becauſe it pleaſed him, Oh Son, to ſet that in the middle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all Souls as a Reward to ſtrive for. And where hath he ſet it? <hi>Hermes.</hi> Filling a large Cup, or Bowl, he ſent it down, giving alſo a Cryer, or Proclaimer, and he commanded him to proclaim theſe things to the Souls of Men. Dip, and waſh thy ſelf thou that art able, in this Cup, or Bowl, thou that believeſt that thou ſhalt return to him that ſent his Cup, thou that acknowledgeſt whereunto thou wert made: As many therefore as underſtood the Proclamation, and were Baptized, or dowſed into the Mind, theſe were made partakers of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36863:10"/>and became perfect Men, receiving the Mind; but as many as miſſed of the Proclamation, they received Speech, but not Mind, being ignorant whereunto they were made, or by whom. But their Senſes are juſt like to bruit Beaſts, and having their temper in Anger and Wrath, they do not admire things worthy, but wholly addicted to the Pleaſures and Deſires of the Bodies; they believe that Man was made for them. But as many as partaked of the gift of God; theſe, Oh Son, in compariſon of their Works, are rather immortal than mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Men, comprehending all things which are upon Earth, and which are in Heaven, and lifting up themſelves ſo high, they ſee the good, and ſeeing it, they accounted it a miſerable Calamity to make their abode here, and deſpiſing all things bodily, and unbodily, they make haſte to the one and only. Thus, Oh Son, is the knowledge of the Mind, the beholding of divine things, and the underſtanding of GOD, the Cup it ſelf being divine. And I, Oh Father, would be baptized and drench'd hearin <hi>Hermes.</hi> Except thou firſt hate thy Body, Oh Son, thou canſt not love thy ſelf, meaning the Soul; but loving thy ſelf, thou ſhalt have the Mind, and having the Mind, thou ſhalt alſo partake of the Knowledge or Science. How meaneſt thou that, Oh Father <hi>Hermes?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is impoſſible, Oh Son, to be converſant about things Mortal and Divine; for the things that are, being two Bodies, and things Incorporeal, where is the Mortal, and the Divine, the Election or choice of either is left to him that will chuſe, for no Man can chuſe both; and of which ſoever the choice is made, the other being climiniſhed or overcome, magnifieth the act: The choice of the better therefore is not only beſt for him that chuſeth it by defying a Man, but it alſo ſheweth Piety and Religion towards GOD, but the choice of the worſt deſtroys a Man; for God is innocent or guiltleſs; but we are the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Evil, preferring them before the good.</p>
            <p>Therefore, whether are you carried, O Men, drunken with drinking up the ſtrong Wine of Ignorance, which ſeeing you cannot bear, why do you not vomit it up again? Stand, and be ſober, Look up again with the eyes of your Heart, for the malice of Ignorance ſurroundeth the Earth, and corrupteth the Soul, ſhut up in the Body, not ſuffering it to ariſe at the Haven of Salvation: Suffer not your ſelves to be carried with the great ſtream, but ſtem the Tide, you that can lay hold of the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Safety, and make your full courſe towards it; ſeek one that may lead you by the hand, and conduct you to the door of Truth, and Knowledge, where the clear Light is, that which is pure from Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, where there is not one drunken, but all are ſober, and in their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36863:11"/>Heart look up to him, whoſe Pleaſure is to be ſeen; for he cannot be heard with Ears, nor ſeen with Eyes, nor expreſſed in words, but only in Mind and Heart.</p>
            <p>But firſt, thou muſt tear in pieces, and break through the Garment thou weareſt, the web of Ignorance, the foundation of all miſchief, the bond of Corruption, the dark Coverture, the living Death, the ſenſible Carkaſs, the Sepulchre carried about with us, the domeſtical Thief, which in what he loves us, hates us, envies us. Such is the hurtful Apparel wherewith thou art cloathed, which draws and pulls thee down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, leſt looking up, and ſeeing the Beauty of Truth, and the good that is repoſed therein, thou ſhouldeſt hate the wickedneſs of this Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and underſtand the traps and ambuſhes which it hath laid for thee, filling what it preſents unto thee with hateful Pleaſures, that thou canſt neither hear what thou ſhouldeſt hear, nor ſee what thou ſhouldeſt to underſtand ſo great a GOD.</p>
            <p>Here you may ſee, what I have delivered to you is no Fancy or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination of my own Brain; no new Doctrine, but what came from the old Aged; for ſo he is called in the old Tranſlation, but in the new, the Auſhout of days. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9. From GOD the ſubſtance of all Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which this excellent ſpirited Man bears Record to, who if we may believe the ancient Writers, this Holy Man lived ſome hundreds of Years before <hi>Moſes</hi>'s time, as is made out in the Epiſtle to the Reader; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of this great Treaſure is ſaid to be found engravened upon a Smaragdine Table, in the Valley <hi>Ebron,</hi> after the Flood: If GOD ever appeared in any Man, ſaith the Epiſtle to the Reader, he appeared in him; that a Man, who had not benefit of his Anc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ors knowledge, being the firſt Inventer of the Art of communicating knowledge to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, by Writing or Engraving, ſhould be ſo deep a Philoſopher, and high a Divine, ſeems to be a thing more of GOD than of Men; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was the opinion of ſome; that he came from Heaven not born upon Earth: The Original, ſaith the Epiſtle, ſo far as is known to us, is <hi>Arabec,</hi> and ſeveral Tranſlations thereof have been publiſhed, as <hi>Greek Latin, French,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> but never <hi>Engliſh</hi> before, by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Doctor <hi>Everard;</hi> ſo far the Epiſtle to the Reader. Behold, how the LORD viſited the Children of Men before the Flood, and by this bleſſed Man's Writing, how the Spirit of God wreſtled and ſtrove, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Meſſengers, as it were, from Heaven, to reform, and reclaim them from their evil ways; but they grieved his holy Spirit, and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Meſſengers, till they had provoked him to ſay, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3.12. <hi>My Spirit ſhall not always ſtrive with Man, but the Breath ſhall ceaſe from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36863:11"/>before me; which I have made!</hi> And then their deſtruction came as a Whirl-wind: And hath it not been the ſame in all Ages? But now the beginning hath near found an end of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; for the Day of the LORD is come, wherein he will do his Wonders of Old, and the Mighty GOD is riſen in the Power of his Might, to plead with all Fleſh, and to deſtroy thoſe from off the Earth that will not be gathered to him in this the day of his Patience and long Suffering; and for this end hath he ſent Meſſenger upon Meſſenger, Embaſſador after Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador to declare His Mind and Will; and not only ſo, but his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are now begun in the Earth, yet the Inhabitants thereof doth not learn Righteouſneſs therefore the deſtroying Angel hath received his Commiſſion, and of this you have been often warned; I am a witneſs for the LORD, he is clear of your Blood; Alſo a few Months ago by a Servant of the LORD's, who came two hundred Miles to deliver this Meſſage, and the thing is come and coming to paſs which he Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of; therefore, Oh King and Queen, for the LORD's ſake, and for His endleſs mercy ſake, <hi>Take the Cenſer,</hi> Numb. 16.46. <hi>and put Fire of the Altar, and Incenſe therein, and haſten with all your Might to make an Attonement for the People, for there is Wrath gone out from the LORD, the Plague is begun both in City and Country.</hi> I am a Witneſs of what my Eyes have ſeen, and Ears heard; therefore, Oh let not the King, who is the Magiſtrate of the Higheſt, bear the Sword of the LORD in vain, but let him be Valiant for the Truth upon Earth, and take the courage of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> the zeal of <hi>Phinehas,</hi> and the humility of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> to go forth in the Strength of the LORD to make War with the Enemies of GOD, that keeps his Divine Majeſty from His Right, to rule in the Souls of the Children of Men, and this ſhall be your preſent and future Happineſs, to ſtop the prophane, and boundleſs flood of Ungodlineſs, that overflows theſe Kingdoms of the King and Queens Dominions; together with that accurſed Idolatrous thing, Covetouſneſs, Hatred, Malice, Deceit, Double-dealing, Lying, Slandring, Cheating, Treachery, betraying Truſts, and Innocence into the hands of Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; beſides all the Sins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; theſe things brought the Wrath and Vengeance of GOD upon them, and theſe Sins cries aloud, yea, louder and louder in the Ears of the LORD GOD, for Plagues, Woes, and Vengeance, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Land, and good reaſon for it. <hi>For you have I known,</hi> ſaith the LORD, <hi>above all the Families of the Earth, therefore will I puniſh you; you have I loaded with my Mercies and Benefits; you have I open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Windows of Heaven to, and ſhowred down Bleſſings upon, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36863:12"/>there hath not been room enough to receive them, you have I brought to a Land that flows with Milk and Honey, and yet this hath been a ſmall thing with me,</hi> ſaith the LORD: <hi>But I have given you the Gifts and Graces of my Holy Spirit, by which you have been made rich with the Knowledge of my Will; but you have deck'd your ſelves with my Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els. Ezek.</hi> 16. and beſtowed my Gifts upon your Lovers, and gone a whoring from me, ſaith the LORD, after your own Inventions; therefore thus ſaith the LORD, <hi>Becauſe you have rewarded me Evils for all my Goodneſs, therfore will I viſit you, and take away my Corn, my Oil, my Wine, my Milk, and my Honey; becauſe you would not ſerve me in the injoyments of all theſe Mercies you ſhall ſerve your Enemies in the want of all theſe, except you ſpeedily repent. O England! England!</hi> What lamentable Lamentation ſhall I take up for Thee, if ever there was a Day to call for the Mourning Women. Now it's come, therefore you that are well skill'd in Mourning. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 9.17, 20. Come away, and do not ſtay, let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hinder you to join with me in this Work with rended Hearts, and bowed down Souls, teach your Daughters to mourn, and every one your Neighbour to lament, that our Eyes caſt out Teers, and Eye-lids guſh out VVater; let us cloath our ſelves in Sackcloth, and roul our ſelves in the Duſt in Faſting and Prayers night and day, crying vehemently and inceſſantly to the Lord, that we may be ready to enter into the Ark, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Flood comes to drown all Earthly Habitations, with their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations. <hi>For all Fleſh hath corrupted its way, therefore the End of all fleſh is come up before the Lord, and by Fire and Sword will God plead with all Fleſh, and the Carkeſſes of men ſhall be as Dung upon the face of the Earth, They ſhall die of Sickneſs and Diſeaſes. I will ſpend mine Arrows on them, and my Sword ſhall devour; yea, Fleſh of Kings Captives, and Potentates of the Earth:</hi> Thus will the Maker of all Things eaſe Himſelf of His Enemies, and avenge Him of His Adverſaries; for, becauſe His Mercy and long Suffering will not humble Sinners, his Righteous Judgements will.</p>
            <p>Therefore, Oh <hi>England! England!</hi> Repent, repent, repent, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what lamentation ſhall be taken up for thee: Oh that my Head were full of water, and my Eyes a Fountain of Teers, that I might weep day and night for the Deſtruction that comes as a VVhirlwind upon Thee, O Land, where the Sins of <hi>Sodom</hi> are found, where the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> are found; where the Sins of <hi>Jamaica</hi> and <hi>Cicilia</hi> are found; In Thee Oh Land, is found the Blood of Innocents, in Thee is found the Cries of the Poor for Juſtice, thou haſt wrong'd the VVidow and Fatherleſs, and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed them of their Right, thou hateſt him that reproves Sin in the Gate, and abhors any that ſpeaketh uprightly, thou haſt crucified the Lord of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36863:12"/>Life afreſh, and in Thee He is put to an open Shame by Profeſſors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, by Thy lewd Abominations, which Thou ſecretly and open I without Shame before the Eyes of His Glory doth commit daily, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one glorying in their Abominations. The Prophane, without Sham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glories in their Swearing, Damning, Drunkenneſs, VVhoring, Laſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Talking, counting him the beſt Man, that is moſt ſtrong and acu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to do all theſe Abominations.</p>
            <p>And on the other hand, the Profeſſors of Religion, there's ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be ſaid that Time would fail to rehearſe: Their Pride, Exceſs in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, following in all things the Faſhions and Cuſtoms of the Heather ſtriving to exceed one another in all manner of Rich and coſtly Atir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Fantaſtical Dreſſes, ſome of them pleading without Shame for then others that are aſhamed, which are but few; ſay, they ſhould be red <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, and not like other People: Surely this is as ſhameleſs as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other.</p>
            <p>For if Chriſt, His Prophets and Apoſtles, had done as you ſay, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do, where had been their Teſtimony among the Multitude againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unfruitful works of Darkneſs, which they were to have no fellowſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> withal, but commanded to reprove them? And where is the Croſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt you are to take up, and your Self-denying Life, you are to follo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt your Pattern in? But your ſelf-ended covering, Oh ye Profeſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will be too ſhort in the Day of account, which is ſwiftly coming, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make you bring forth your Talent, which you ſlothfully and maliciouſly have hid in the Earth, and then receive your Portion among the Hipo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</p>
            <p>The next to your Habit is your Houſes, which are deck'd with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Curioſity, Richneſs and Delicacy, as your ſinful Perſons are: You great ſpacious Lordly Houſes, furniſhed with all manner of coſtly, ric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſumptuous Furniture, which would be too tedious, and fill up muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Paper to inſiſt upon; but your voluptuous Feeding, and exceſſive Feaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ing one another, in ſo much that you run out great Eſtates, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your own and other Men's; but in your own Families, that is, amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ervants, many of you are very pinching and ſparing, and to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Poor little or nothing, but what you are compell'd to in your Pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Duties; and your poor Neighbours, many hundreds in City and Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> try, ſits in their Houſes with hungry Bellies, both of Weavers an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> others, that knows not which way to ſhift for Bread for their Children ſome eating Bread ſparingly, and drink Water, Others getting Gard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtuff, as Cabbage, and ſuch like for their Children to feed on; whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you feed, <hi>Dives</hi> like, lying at your Eaſe, ſtretching your ſelves upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:36863:13"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ur rich Sattin Beds and Couches, wallowing in all your ſinful Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es, not knowing what to Eat, Drink, or put on for Richneſs and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>inties; and others of you Hoards up Treaſure as Sand, and are n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſatisfied, compaſſing Sea and Land to get Riches, adding Houſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouſe, and Land to Land, and all for Portions for our Children, ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ey; and thus the Fathers eat ſowre Grapes, and the Childrens Teeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſet an edge. Thus the Parents makes the Children to fould more: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Children of Hell than themſelves, by giving them that that proves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ares, to fulfil their Luſts in Pride and Avarice; and ſo your Childrens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>od muſt lie at your doors: But ſometimes it falls out, that neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nor your Children are Poſſeſſors of what you have pawn'd your Souls, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> made your Bodies and Minds Drudges and Slaves to the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ous Mammon; for on a ſudden the Hand of the LORD ſweeps it all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ay: This I have ſeen in my time, and juſt is the LORD to take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ay your Idols, your Gods of Silver and Gold, and then your Honours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſt fall in the Duſt. But what think you that calls your ſelves Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s? Was this the End of your Creation? Did God create you for this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d to ſerve your Luſts? And you that pretends to be called out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orld, that is, to ſeparate your ſelves from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat think you? Is this the End of your Calling, to bury your ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Earth, to run a whoring from the LORD after your Idols, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ur Gods of Silver and Gold, your Earthly Minds? Are not you of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rth Earthly? Was this the End of your Calling, to take up your Reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> great Houſes, great Trades, great Gain? That you may conſume it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> your Luſt, your Pride, faſhioning your ſelves after the Modes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Heathen, ſome in Rich and Gorgious Atire, others in plainer, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ch and coſtly, and both you ſtrive to exceed one another in Princely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouſes, ſtately Furniture, your Braſs and Irons muſt glitter in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es, like the furbiſhed Gold and Silver; your Cabinets ſhines, that if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>u wanted Looking-Glaſſes you might view your Pride in them, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oards of your Rooms ſo exceeding white or ſhining brown, that a clean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ind knows not how to tread on them. Now you that are Diſſenters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>om the Church of all Sorts and Sects, from the Presbiter to the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endant, from the Independant to the Baptiſt, from the Baptiſt to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uaker; View your ſelves here, and ſee how far you differ from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurch of <hi>England</hi> in the Practical Part; and becauſe you are all one in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ur Lives and Converſations, therefore you muſt have your Portions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> gether: For what though you are all crying low here, and low there, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e ſaith in this Form, and another ſaith in that Form GOD is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>orſhipped in, and they that will not ſit down with you in your Forms,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36863:13"/>you perſecute them, ſo far as your Power goes, to Death if poſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with your Tongues, where the Poyſon of Aſps are under, and ſharp than a two edged Sword to ſlay the Innocent. All be it, the LOR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath ſaid, <hi>The Innocent and Righteous, thou ſhalt not ſlay,</hi> and thoſe that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not what you would have them to be, to my knowledge ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you will not ſuffer them to buy nor ſell; And is not this the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Beaſt? But wherein do you differ from the Church of <hi>England</hi> Except that formerly they were more liberal to the Poor, than y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in building Alms-houſes, and allowing a conſtant maintenance f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, which indeed, hath been much more formerly than now; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is with them as it is with you, becauſe Iniquity doth abound, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the love of many grow cold. But you Covetous, Earthly minde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Profeſſors of all ſorts, your niggardly pinching the Poor, your givin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> five, ten, twenty or Forty Shillings, nay, five, ten, twenty Pounds<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (though who is ſo liberal) will not excuſe you that have Hundreds, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thouſands, and many Thouſands lying by a year will not excuſe you befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the LORD of the whole Earth, when His Majeſty calls you to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count what you have done with his Treaſure he committed to you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Truſt, to ſerve him, and his Creation: Will you ſay, we hoarded i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up by us; or will you ſay, We gave it our Children for their Por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to live in Pride and Luxury; Then will the LORD of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſay, You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ennogades, durſt you preſume to run a Whoring afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your Idols, ſpending your precious time in hunting after the treaſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of my Earth, though to the hazzarding my utter diſpleaſure? Becauſe you went not in my Counſel, nor waited in my Fear, to know my Mind and Will in your gettings, and when you ſhould ceaſe from the incumbrance of the World, that when you had got ſufficient for Food and Raiment, you ſhould therewithal have been contented: For I have ſaid, <hi>I will never leave, nor forſake them that walks in my Fear.</hi> But if I had bleſſed you with over-plus, then to have waited upon me for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Counſel how to order the reſt to ſerve me in my Members, making plentiful Proviſion, not only for them of your own Judgment, but for all ſorts, that the Widow, Fatherleſs, and Strangers may have no want, that they may be the fitter to ſerve me their Creator, in all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and Holy Reverence. But I may ſay to you, as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>You baſtardly Generation of Chriſtians, who are Strangers to his Sowſhip;</hi> How comes it that you muſt enjoy all the good things of God's Creation? Did the wiſe Diſpoſer of all things give you the precious things of his Creation for to ſpend them upon your Luſts? Was it ſo in the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning? O no. Yet GOD ſaw in the Beginning what would enſue,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36863:14"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Man, that was without the Knowledge of GOD, was left to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he would be like the Beaſt that periſheth; therefore, the wiſe Creator, in his Eternal Wiſdom made a Law for a limit to his unbridled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt, by ſeveral Precepts and Injunctions in the Law, where he expreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y tied them by ſeveral diſtinct Precepts to very large Contributions, and Communications of their Eſtates, mounting in all, it may be, to more than a ſixth part of their Yearly Incomes; And was there ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are taken then by that which was imperfect? How much more now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught there to be by them that are come to the Law of Chriſt, that fulfils all Righteouſneſs, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy ſelf;</hi> for Chriſt is the end of the Law, in Him the Law is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>illed; likewiſe, thoſe that are come to Chriſt, and put Him on, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re regenerated, and born again, they are become new; old things are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt away, and all things are become new; the old Covetous, Earthly Spirit is taken away, and a noble, generous, free Spirit in the room, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike their LORD and Maſter, who gives liberally, and upbraids <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one, but feeds and cloaths his Enemies richly and bountifully, and who are Chriſtians indeed, are like him; as witneſs, when his Spirit was poured out from on high, how they ſold their Poſſeſſions, and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uted to every one as they had need but the Covetous died the Death; as <hi>Saphira</hi> and his Wife, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.2. who dealt deceitfully with GOD and his People, in keeping back the Lord's due, when he required it. Conſider this, you that forgets God, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you: But you Worldlings of all ſorts, you have had a long time to conſider theſe things, from one Generation to another, and though you have heard and ſeen your Brother Worldlings taken away before your Eyes ſuddenly, without Repentance, yet this will not ſtop you from your eagerly graſping up together with the Expence of your moſt precious Time, which is worth a VVorld up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a dying Bed, when Conſcience is awakened, and inſtead of giving up your Strength and Might to wait upon the LORD, with all diligence, crying mightily to Him for His Power and Strength, to creſiſt all the Temptations of Sinful Fleſh; you give up your Strength, Might and Care, to graſp and heap up Riches, as if all your happineſs whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſted in the abundance of the things you enjoy in this Life; ſo that here you deny Chriſt, his Doctrine and Practice, who ſaid. <hi>No Man can ſerve two Maſters.</hi> Ye cannot ſerve ſaid he, GOD and Riches; therefore I ſay untoyou, <hi>Be not careful for your Life what ye ſhall eat, or what ye ſhall drink, nor yet for your Body what ye ſhall put on;</hi> and then ſend you to the Fowls of Heaven, and the Flowers of the Field to learn of them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36863:14"/>your Duty to him. Oh! ye Worldlings of all ſorts, How far ſhort are you of being obedient to theſe Heavenly Precepts, and the fulfilling this precious Doctrine? You Wealth-mongers who hurry you ſelves almoſt out of your Wits to get Money, the love of which is the Root of all Evil, laying Bag to Bag, till it comes to Hundreds and Thouſands: But how much have you laid by to ſerve the Lord, and your Fellow-Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Neceſſity, it may be, five, ten, twenty Shillings, and in this you would be counted Liberal, and by ſome poor Creatures that are in great Neceſſity you are ſo; but in the Eyes of the Lord you are counted Vile and Churliſh: But, Oh! ye Hard-hearted Profeſſors and Cruel of all ſorts, that ſuffers your Fellow-Creatures that are made of the ſame Fleſh, Blood and Bones that you are made of, ſome to Starve, and others to want Food and Raiment, and you have your Hundreds and Thouſands. But what is the Reaſon of theſe things? Why the ſame Reaſon may be given, that was to the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old. This People hath an unfaithful and rebellious Heart, they are departed and gone, for they ſay not in their Hearts, <hi>Let us now fear the Lord our God that gives Rain both early and late, in due Seaſon, he that reſerveth to us the appointed Weeks of the Harveſt.</hi> Yet, ſaith God, your Iniquities have turned away theſe things, and your Sins hath with-held good things from you.</p>
            <p>For amongſt my People are found wicked Perſons, that lay wait as he that ſetteth Snares, they have made a Pit to catch Men, as a Cage is full of Birds, ſo are their Houſes full of Deceit: Thereby they are become Great, and waxen Rich, they are waxen fat and ſhining; they do over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the Deeds of the Wicked, they execute no Judgment, no not the Judgment of the Widow and Fatherleſs, yet they proſper, though they Execute no Judgment for the Poor. <hi>Shall I not viſit for theſe things,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>or ſhall not my Soul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this.</hi> Oh <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, London,</hi> how often hath this Scripture been brought to me for thee, and for thy Inhabitance, Oh! Land. <hi>Jerem. chap.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Shall not my Soul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this: And upon the like occaſion in another place, ſaith he, <hi>Ye I will feed this People with Wormwood, and give them the Waters of Gaul to drink,</hi> Jerem. 9.15. And did he not avenge his righteous Cauſe upon <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and did he not give them Waters of Gaul to drink when he did deſtroyed them, and their Pride, Luſts, Cruelty, Hard heartedneſs, Covetous, Earthly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and altogether; and do you think to eſcape the righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, that knows all theſe things and yet live in the ſame Sins to provoke the Eyes of his Glory: No, you ſhall ſurely drink of the ſame Cap except you ſpeedily repent, the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36863:15"/>and your outward Services, your outſide Profeſſion of God and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, your Religious Duties, your Holy Orders. From the Throne to the Dunghill in Profeſſion out of the Life of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſhall not be able to deliver you from the Plagues and Judgments that is to come, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpeedily upon this Land, without a ſincere Repentence, for the Earth groans to be deliver'd of ſuch Hipocrites, ſuch uſeleſs Branches that brings forth no Fruit neither to God nor Man. But again, to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy Soul with all thy Strength, withall thy Might, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> for upon theſe two hang the Law and the Prophets: So then here is the very ſtint of Religion, now how far this goes muſt be examined into. And God ſaid <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me;</hi> now if it had not been for this Command, the Fleſh might have ſaid, Theſe are thy Gods Oh <hi>Iſrael</hi> that brought thee out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> thy Silver, Gold and precious Stones hath wrought all thy wonderful and unheard-of Deliverances; for you know they made a Calf of their Treaſures, and danc'd about it, whilſt <hi>Moſes</hi> was with God in the Mount receiving a Law againſt all ſuch Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations: And now the Lord of the whole Earth is come again to ſearch out the Iniquity of our Times, and are not you found in the ſame Steps of your Fore-fathers, ſerving your Gods of Silver and Gold, and all worſhiping the Works of our own hands, admiring your ſelves, ways and works, Adoring them as Gods, although the LORD hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me:</hi> So here is the Breach of this Command, and alſo of the other two; for Chriſt ſaid we cannot ſerve GOD and <hi>Mamon,</hi> therefore if you give your Love to any of theſe, GOD cannot have All: Then how much leſs hath he when all your hearts, all your Souls, all your Strengths, all your Mights, all your Loves and Delights is given up to ſerve your Idols of Silver and Gold, your Pride, Self-Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rſts, Glories and Honours; theſe have your Hearts, theſe have your Loves and Delights, and whilſt theſe your periſhing Gods have all, the Everlaſting GOD your Creator and Maker muſt have none. And thus you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God of his Right, and turns his Glory into ſhame; and again, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf:</hi> Pray conſider how far this Command ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, for Chriſt brings it into an equal Competition; do you ſuffer your ſelves to want any Food or Raiment, or other Neceſſaries that is fitting for your outward Body to ſerve its Neceſſities, the ſame care you ſhould take for your Neighbour, that their Bodies and Minds might be the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſerve their Maker with all humble Thanks-giving; and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do unto you, do ye that unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36863:15"/>
            <p>I humbly gave the Queen in writing how the aforeſaid might be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd, but if your are wanting in this your Duty to your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, how will you perform the weighty Matters of the Law, for this is, as it were, but the External Service, the outſide Duty of Chriſtianity, yet no Chriſtians, nor no Exceptance with <hi>Chriſt</hi> without it, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> calls the Unrighteous <hi>Mamon, Wherein,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if you are unfaithful, who ſhall commit to you the true Riches;</hi> ſo that when you have performed all the Will of God in this point, and made your Neighbour equal, ſo far as I have treated of: Nay, if you ſhall give all your Goods to the Poor, as ſome have done, that have not had that knowledge of God, that you have which ſhames you, and will be a ſwift Witneſs againſt you in the Day of Account: yet hear as I ſaid before, you muſt not reſt, for this is but one part of your Duty of Chriſtianity: the neglect of which hath been the cauſe of ſo many Thieves and Robbers in the Land: This is the outward Service that is not to be left undone. But there is further Service, an inward Service, wherein you muſt give your ſelves all up to GOD for him to work in you all his good pleaſure, whereby he may transform thee into himſelf, to be made like unto him in all things. But, for the carrying on of this Great Work, thou muſt wait upon GOD in ſilence, in the ſilence of all fleſh, and ſuffer him to ſpeak: pray work and do all in thee, for hear the LORD will diſrobe thee of all thy Gifts and Parts, and ſtrip thee ſtark naked as ever thou was born; <hi>For naked thou cam'ſt into the World, and naked muſt thou return.</hi> Stript not only of thy filthy Garments ſpotted by the Fleſh; but all the Riches of thy Spirit, before thou art clothed with change of Raiment, the rich Robes of Eternal Life; for it is the poor in Spirit that receives the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Hear the Soul ſtands naked, having nothing of its own, neither Words nor Works to preſent it ſelf before the LORD: nothing but its Poverty, its Nothingneſs, its Inſufficiency, bringing all its little Ones before the Eyes of his Glory, to move His Excellency, to caſt His Eye of Mercy and tender Compaſſion, and ſpread the Skirt of His Eternal Love over it. Here's the place where GOD will work Wonders: hear he will ariſe in the Power of His Might, and make bare His Glorious Arm for the Soul's deliverance. Hear the higheſt makes a Covenant with His <hi>Jehoſhuas,</hi> His choſen Ones, ſaying, <hi>If you will walk in my ways and keep my watch, then thou ſhalt Judge mine Houſe, and ſhalt alſo keep my Courts, and I will give thee a place among them that ſtand.</hi> Zacharia chap. 3.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:36863:16"/>
            <p>Here's the Reward of all your Travels, of all your Warfare, of all Wreſtlings, of all your Holy Violence to take the Kingdom of Heaven by force: Here's the Reward of ſelf-denial and ſelf-abhorrence, for the Soul that would be united to Chriſt, muſt be conformable to Him, following him in the ways of His internal Sufferings, that purifies the Soul from the pollutions both of Fleſh and Spirit, and hear it arrives at the Myſtical ſilence, where he ſpeaks to it alone in the moſt ſecret and hidden parts of the Heart, where He teaches it the moſt perfect and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halted Wiſdom; therefore thou art to keep thy ſelf in this Myſtical ſilence, if thou wilt hear this ſecret and heavenly Voice: for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Soul conſiſts not in ſpeaking much of GOD, but in Obedience and in loving Him, ſo much as belongs to Him, and you know how much CHRIST ſaith that is: But your ſilent ſublime Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation is that <hi>Elias</hi> was in, when he heard the ſtill ſoft Voice in <hi>Horch,</hi> the <hi>Mount of GOD:</hi> which ſignifies the Mount of Regeneration, where the Soul is retired and ſhut up in GOD from all the hurrings and buſiles of the World, and the deeper its gets into this innermoſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the more dead it is, not only to the World and the Concerns thereof, but to it ſelf in all things whether External or Internal, it ſerves the very neceſſity of Nature with Grief, thinking all time to much that is ſpent in any thing, but in waiting upon GOD alone; and this is its continual Exerciſe to enter into it ſelf, there to abide with GOD in perfect Unity and Reſignation, and being ſo diſintereſted and taken off from ſelf, that though it ſhould fulfill all the Commands of CHRIST that concerns GOD and its Neighbour, and ſhould leave nothing undone of the Duty of a true Chriſtian; yet, it makes no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all this before His Divine Majeſty; nay, tho' they being in ſuch an Eſtate as to receive many wonderful Gifts and ſupernatural Graces; yet they are not lifted up with vain conceit, nor prides them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in theſe rich Robes, but are juſt as if they had received no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, being always humbled in the depth of their own unworthineſs, and ever kept in a holy Fear and inflaimed Love to GOD; which ſhews that the Creature exhalted in Gifts, is <hi>Lucifer:</hi> But the Soul thus adorned with Heavenly Graces in the Humility, is CHRIST JESUS come again in the Fleſh; therefore this is the Spirit that is to be uppermoſt, whether in Proſperity or Adverſity if you would have GOD to be your Teacher; for the humble GOD will teach: I mean the Humility of CHRIST who em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptied Himſelf of all His Glory both Heavenly and Earthly, and humbled himſelf to the death both in Body and Mind, <hi>John</hi> 30. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. and 44. both in Soul and Body were his ſufferings: And if we are his Diſciples, we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36863:16"/>muſt tread in His ſteps, we muſt firſt die to ſelf, before we can live to God: the true Figure is a Corn of Wheat, ſaith CHRIST, <hi>John</hi> 12.24. and the more dead the Creature is in it ſelf, and to it ſelf, the more it ſhall know and pleaſe GOD: but if it doth not mind this continual denying of ſelf and internal Mortification, it will never arrive at this ſtate of perfection; but through this Baptiſm of Fire and the Holy Ghoſt, this inward Hearts-breaking, Soul-ſuffering, theſe Faithful Ones comes to waſh there long-ſuffering Robes, and makes them white in the Blood of the Lamb, for theſe are redeemed from the Earth and all periſhing and tranſitory Things; and therefore have the Harps of GOD in their hands to ſing the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Lamb: for from theſe internal Soul-ſufferings, comes the Eternal Heavenly Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Joys; therefore lift up your Heads ye tribulated Ones, that are ſurrounded with Sorrows both within and without: look up to the Rock whence ye are hewn; but look not to Man for help, whoſe Breath is in his Noſtrils, for then it will be juſt with the Higheſt to ſay to you, as he did to them of Old, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.28. call upon your Gods, let them deliver you; but look unto me, ſaith the Everlaſting, all ye ends of the Earth and be ſaved: but look not at the Creature how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they may be ſuffered to try and prove you; but keep your Eye to your Saviour's Beauty, which is Patience, Meekneſs, and Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, let theſe be ever in your Eye; but caſt not your Eye upon the Inſtrument, who, or whatſoever they may be, for that will beget anger and wrath in your minds, and then you will looſe the end of your Sufferings; for all theſe things are ſuffered to be to wean you off the Creatures, to let you ſee the emptineſs and nothingneſs of all things that hath a begining even to your ſelves, and this is the way to make GOD all, and the poor empty Creature nothing.</p>
            <p>But whatſoever your Tryal is, or with whomſoever, be ſhure, you keep in the Love that thinks no Evil, no, not to the greateſt of all your Enemies, and then you will be ready upon all Occaſions to do them any Office of Love, as the Power is in your hands, and their Neceſſity requires, and thus you will fulfill the Royal Law of CHRIST your Lord, who ſaid love your Enemies, do Good for Evil, overcome Evil with Good, that you may be the Children of your Heavenly Father, who cauſes His Glorious Sun to ſhine upon the Juſt and the Unjuſt, and ſo your Prayer ſhall be heard, when you ſay, <hi>Lord forgive us our treſpaſſes againſt thee, as we forgive them there treſpaſſes againſt us;</hi> and thus will the Righteous Judge of the whole Earth, take the Cauſe of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent in His Hands and plead it with their Enemies, for vengeance is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36863:17"/>mine, ſaith the Lord, and I will repay, for it is as <hi>Dindimus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, <hi>He is a Judge of all injuries, and the Sighs of thoſe that are injuriouſly treated, become the pain of thoſe that injure them.</hi> But as was ſaid before to you Servants of the LORD, whom he hath coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy to be partakers with Him of His Internal and External Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings to be rejected of all, denied, condemned, and tempted within and without, in Fears and Dreads, in Weakneſs, in Watchings and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, with Tears of ſorrow Night and Day; led into the Wilderneſs and there tempted, tried in the Night with great Temptations, led in a Way you know not, nor ſee no way out; but as it were paſſing by the Gates of Hell, and none pitty nor take your part: Hear your Love to GOD will be prov'd to the uttermoſt, whether you will follow your beloved LORD and holy JESUS in His ſuffering Life, who trod the Wine-preſs alone, and of the People there was none with him; who was compaſſed with Sorrows on every ſide: He that was in ſuch a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth of ſorrows as never Man was, he ſaw no comfort neither in Life nor Death, above him nor below him from God or Men; were our Condition as bad as his, if it were poſſible that we were in the very midſt of the heat and fire of Affliction, when the flood of Temptation ariſes an hundred fold above your ſtrongeſt hold, yet here you may be at reſt in your beloved LORD, in an aſſured confidence that all things ſhall work together for your good that loves the LORD, although you may cry out and ſay, as I know a Soul that did, <hi>Was ever any Sorrows like unto mine? Did ever any go this Way before me?</hi> The immediate Anſwer was, <hi>Yes,</hi> Moſes, <hi>and all the Prophets, and JESUS the author and finiſher thereof:</hi> Therefore thou art compaſſed about with a cloud of Witneſſes, when upon an inviſible ſight, I ſaid, <hi>O my God, Muſt there be yet more fire?</hi> then He ſaid unto me, <hi>In the Fire and in the Water I will be with thee, and make thy way thorow all.</hi> I believed the LORD, and was ſtrengthened, and his powerful Word was my Salvation: Therefore you that are brought into theſe fiery Trials, have a care you murmur not, neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire his hand to be removed till all is conſumed, that is, for the Fire in this fiery Baptiſm, and if you continue faithful to the end of your Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in Patience and Long-ſuffering, diligently attending upon His Hand alone, for His redeeming Power to redeem you from the Earth, and all periſhing things, <hi>whoſe Fan is in his hand, and he will thoroughly purge his Floor, and gather his Wheat into his Gardner, but the Chaff he will hurn up in this unquenchable fire,</hi> and then you ſhall come forth as the Gold ſeven times refined: And farther, take this from one that hath upon Tryal proved it, for your comfort and encouragement in your Journy,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36863:17"/>that the more diligently you wait upon him in all Conditions you paſs through, even ſo much the more ſhall you receive of his virtuous Life, and heavenly Power, for by this your continual ſecreet converſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Union with the Everlaſting GOD; you will come to be ſo filled with his divine Love, that your Mortal will be ſwallowed up of the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, ſo that it will become your whole Life, and all your Thoughts, Words and Works will have their Rice and ſettled Habitation therein, but then you muſt be ſure let nothing come out of the fire unconſumed; for hear lies the ſtreſs of all, your giving up all, that which is for the Sword to be cut off, and that that is for the Fire to be burnt up; for if you keep any thing back that GOD requires to be offered up, of any Darling-ſin, or beloved <hi>Dalalie;</hi> whether Love to the World, Name or Fame, together with the whole Catalogue that belongs to Self, for if Self be in any caſe whatſoever, you muſt lay the Ax to the Root of that Tree, and with all your Strength and Power cut it down, for if the Root remains, the fruitleſs Tree will grow, therefore Self the accurſed Thing muſt be found out and deſtroyed. <hi>Joſhua</hi> 7.11.22. <hi>Before you can proſper in this Holy War, to get the Victory over all your Enemies, for you know a faithful Souldier intangles not himſelf with the Affairs of this Life, but gives up all to follow him that hath choſen him, counting nothing dear to them, nor any thing hard to endure for the hope of obtaining the Victory,</hi> and I entreat you conſider how intent he is in the Fight, Doth he mind any thing but ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at the Enemy? No, for if he did, he could not overcome, it is ſo in the ſpiritual Warfare of the Soul: It counts nothing dear that it may win him CHRIST JESUS, thinking no time long, nor any thing hard to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, for the Joy and Beauty that is ſet before it; of its beloved Lord, who went before through the bitter Agony of Soul, and bloody Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, with Mockings, Slanders, Reproaches, Hatred and Malice of his cruel Enemies, and ignominious Death for thee, and the Redemption of thy Soul from all Iniquity, if thou follow Him the Captain of thy Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, through his ſelf-denial in Faith and Obedience; for it is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given you to believe, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake, <hi>Becauſe Faith without Works is dead,</hi> and thus the LORD will be found in his own way, <hi>For I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life, and none can come to the Father but by me,</hi> ſaith he: Here you ſee CHRIST is the Way, his ſuffering Life is the Way he hath appointed, and alſo ſaith, <hi>He that comes this Way to me, I will in no wiſe caſt him off, but will pray to the Father that whatſoever you ask the Father in my Name he will give it you, even the Spirit of Truth that ſhall lead you into all Truth, and cut of all Errour, and will be your Strength in all Weakneſs, for this is that your Souls travels for, and hath ſuch bitter Pang
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36863:18"/>as a Woman in Travail, to bring forth my Will, my moſt exceptable Will, therefore will I deliver you, and though you ſowe in Tears you ſhall reap in Joy, and tho' you go out weeping and carrying precious Seed, you ſhall return with Joy, and bring your Sheaves,</hi> 126 Pſalm. 5, 6.</p>
            <p>As one ſpeaking his own Experience with Chriſt's words, ſaid, <hi>For though Sin the evil Seed be ſown when Men ſleep, and take root with Pleaſure, and ſprings up with Delight, yet the End thereof is Bitterneſs, Lamentation, and unconceivable Wooes:</hi> But my precious Seed, ſaith Chriſt, is ſown with Tears, conceived with Sorrow, and brought forth with Sighings, Nights of Watchings, Days of Mourning, and with much labour of Spirit, and travail of Soul muſt you ſee your deſire Brought forth; and its not beating the Air that will fight your battels, for its a gainſt ſuch airy Notions you are to make War, and all Spirits of what ſorts ſoever that would poſſeſs you with Words and Forms without the power of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs regard them not, for nothing leſs than Victory over Sin will ſatisfie your immortal Souls: Therefore yours is Work, and not vain Words, and for my part all's a like to me, whether in Forms, or out of Forms, if they deny the power of Godlineſs in the Practical-part. I ſay, as the Apoſtle ſaid <hi>From ſuch turn away,</hi> and do as Chriſt, my LORD and Maſter did, turn from the proud <hi>Phariſees</hi> to the poor <hi>Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> and <hi>Sinners,</hi> that wants a Phyſician, and tender his loving kindneſs to them, for the whole needs no Phyſician but the Sick, and what tho ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may ſay we have Eat and Drank in thy preſence; nay farther, caſt our Devils, and in thy Name done many wonderful Works, but what ſaid Chriſt to all this, <hi>Depart from me ye workers of Iniquity, I know you not.</hi> This is plain and evident for you to ſee, if you are not wilfully blind, its not all the outward Services of the outward Temple, nor the outward Water, nor the Holy Duties, nor the holy and comply Orders, for the worker iniquity hath ſpoiled all theſe, and made them unholy and uncomly, But the latter of theſe might uave claim'd more right to the aforeſaid wonderfull works: had they kept to their firſt works, and in the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of Chriſt. But what they had committed to them when they were in poverty of ſpirit, they have decked themſelves therewith, and now it ſerves to make a diſcourſe of, though they are gone from the Life of Innocency into the ſpirit of Craft and ſubtilty, and ſo are got above the Croſs of Chriſt, which is the power of GOD, into the Liberty of of the Fleſh, by which they are become Great and waren <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich and ſo bleſs themſelves in the Earth inſtead of the GOD of Trueth. This is Adultery, Treachery and Whordom, therefore their Portion is with the reſt, <hi>Depart from me ye workers of Iniquity, I know you not:</hi> Others there
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36863:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>are who have a Sight beyond Forms, but the ſame Ground remains in them, as in the reſt, very few excepted that I know of; yet a more univerſſal Spirit of Love to all remains in them than the reſt.</p>
            <p>Friends to you this is my Advice, Take not up your reſt in your ſights, tho they ſhould reach to the Third-heaven, without this life of Chriſt, I have been a treating of; and this I can aſſure you it will be more for your profit when you come together to ſit in Dumb-ſilence, than to ſpend your precious time in Diſcourſes of your Attainments; for what are all your Attainments but airy Notions if you come not to the life of Chriſt, for how many have ſeen the good Land that never entred it; and this know, That Viſions and Revelations may ceaſe, for how many have I heard of, and knew ſome that have had all theſe, and yet lives evil Lives, witneſs <hi>Balam,</hi> who from his ſight deſired to die the <hi>Death of the rightous,</hi> and <hi>that his laſt End might be as his:</hi> yet through Coveteouſneſs, which is Idolatry, by his Counſel cauſed <hi>Iſrael</hi> to commit Sin againſt the Lord: tho' to his and their own Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Therefore this is a ſandy Foundation to build on, but if you build on CHRIST, the Corner-ſtone, the tried precious and Elected-ſtone, choſen for that uſe whom the Maſter <hi>Babel-builders</hi> have rejected, which is the cauſe of all their Confuſion, theſe have conceived a Faith in the air, and therefore bring forth nothing but Storms, and peſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious Winds, ſtriving without Foundations, and ſo are driven to and frow, but brings nothing to perfection, and therefore muſt be all thrown down, and not one ſtone left upon another before the <hi>Holy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> which cometh down from God, can be; but therefore as was ſaid Sights, Viſions and Revelation are little worth, but to condemn thoſe that have them, if they do not anſwer the End for which they were given them, to wit, a holy, pure, and undefiled life, which is the End of all gifts.</p>
            <p>And farther, I know a Soul could write a Volume of Sights, Viſions and Revelations which ſhe hath had above theſe thirty Years, and ſome that were given highly to juſtifie her Ways and Works when ſhe was little in her own Eyes, and nothing in her own ſight, it may be Judging and condemning her ſelf for that which he in his Exalted Power hath juſtified her, and for confirmation hath taken her upin to the boſom of his love where ſhe injoyed cloſe and amorous Embraces, His ſealing to her the precious promiſes of His Glorious Life and Eternal Love.</p>
            <p>And now among the many Sights, Viſions, and Revelations, ſhe may inſtant one in three Years abſtainency, ſomtimes faſting two Days and two Nights together, ſometimes three Days and three
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36863:19"/>Nights, and at the time of this ſight, three Days and three or four Nights together, ſhe being at this time in great Travail of Soul, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in Body, with conflicts of Spirit, ſhe poured out her Complaint before the LORD, and ſaid: <hi>Oh!</hi> my LORD, <hi>If I have found favour in thy ſight, and what I have done be pleaſing unto thee, ſhew a Token of Good to thy Hand-maid, that may be as an Anchor to my poor troubled Soul:</hi> And that very Night ſhe had a Viſion of an inviſible Glory, which is too long to inſert here, but how it was with her is as followeth.</p>
            <p>Her Sences were all ſhut up in GOD, ſhe was, in cloſs Communion with the LORD, ſhe was as ſhe thought, wholly deſolved out of the Earthly into the heavenly, ſhe thought ſhe was as an innocent Child new born, and though ſhe had faſted ſo long together, yet ſhe was filled, as with new Wine, and the heavenly <hi>Manna,</hi> by the ſtrength of which ſhe declared the great things of GOD's holy Law, of his Royal Acts, and of his heavenly Power, and ſhe was filled with his Praiſe, and then no Tongue can tell nor Pen write how it was with her, for ſhe was as if ſhe had had a new Body given her in Innocency, Joy and Content, as it were, quite tranſlated out of the Old into the New, all over in raviſhing Joy, filled with unutterable, harmonious Praiſes, ſo lying for many hours in this heavenly Tranſportation; a heavenly Silence came over all, and in this Silence theſe Words were ſpoken aloud to her. <hi>This is the Reſt wherein I will cauſe the Weary to reſt; this is the Life of the Innocent Swain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this was the Token of Good ſhe required, which the LORD in his endleſs Love Anſwered; This, and above a hundred times more which ſhe never took up her Reſt in, though her Sights were attended with his raviſhing Life, for theſe heavenly Manſions are given as a Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to draw the Soul of the down-ward Earth up-ward, to fix it ſelf in GOD the Fountain of all theſe raviſhing Streams and Beams that comes from his glorious Son of Rightouſneſs, lifting up himſelf in the Soul to draw it after him, as Himſelf ſaid, <hi>When the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of Man is lifted up, He will draw all Men after Him.</hi> But the time is not yet come that He will draw all Men after him, therefore we muſt wait for the Day of his Power, we muſt wait at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for the Promiſe of the Father, which is, that He will pour out His Spirit upon all Fleſh, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> for hetherto the higheſt Attainment that hath attended the Life of CHRIST, hath been but a glimps of that Glory that is ready to break forth were we but ready for it: But is this the way for the Bride to make her ſelf ready to meer the Bridegroom, for her to pride her ſelf with the Bridegroom's gifts, and that her rich Attier ſhould be the cauſe to take her Love and Affections off her Bridegroom, who ſhould be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36863:19"/>clean, humble and chaſt to meet her Lord: Thus the Harlot having o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Attire is taking for the chaſt Spouſe and virtuous Bride; but the Day of her Diſcovery is at hand, wherein ſhe ſhall be ſtript naked and bare, and then her ſhame will appear to all.</p>
            <p>But to the aforeſaid Attainments, the greateſt of which hath been but as the Voice of one crying in the Wilderneſs prepare the Way of the LORD, and make ſtraight ways in the Deſert, for all that hath been he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto muſt lay their Mouths in the Duſt, and ſay, as <hi>Iohn Baptis, I am not be, nor worthy to unlcoſe his Shooe-latchet becauſe I muſt Decreaſe, but He muſt Increaſe;</hi> Therefore this is the Work of our Day, to know the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of his Grace, of which there ſhall be no End; to know in our Souls and Bodies the fellowſhip of his Sufferings, and to be Baptized into his Death, and then we ſhall know the Reſurrection of his Glorious Life, the <hi>Lamb of GOD, that taketh away the Sins of the World; who ſhall change our vile Bodies, and make them like his glorious Body, to praiſe Him Evermore, World without End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more I have diſcharged my ſervice to GOD, and Duty to you, not of my one Mind, or Will, for had it ſtood with my Will I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been concern'd more with this Generation, after I had delivered the three firſt books to the King and Queen, but having delivered the laſt of the three, Titled to Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> going in <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> the precious preſence of the LORD accompaning Me, being filled with Joy, and returning thanks to the LORD for his great goodneſs, and manifold Mercies in given me power and ſtrength to do his exceptable Will, and finding my ſelf clear, as I thought, of the Blood of all; I communed thus with the LORD in deep humility, That if I had found favour in his ſight, and that I had finiſhed the Work he had given me to do: then I might return to him in peace, <hi>for my Eyes had ſeen his Salvation;</hi> Upon theſe Words a mighty Power fell upon me, that operated in all parts of my Body, and a ſtrong powerful Voice Said, <hi>Ariſe and thraſh, Oh Daughter of</hi> Sion, <hi>for I will make thy Horn, Iorn, and thy Hoof, Braſs:</hi> Upon theſe Words, I was greatly bowed down in deep humility, weeping before the LORD, and humbly beging his aſſiſting Power and heavenly Wiſdom to fulfil His holy devine Will in all things, that His pleaſure was to require of me: Then after this I wrote another Printed-book to the King and Queen, and four Papers in writing at ſeveral times, which I delivered into their one hands; and then after I had delivered thoſe Writings, I wrote another Book, which I had almoſt finiſhed; but this coming ſo forceable upon me, I laid that by, and this hath been longer in hand than I expected when I begun it, for indeed all things looking ſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36863:20"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ark and diſmal, I rather expected ſome dreadful Judgment would break <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth before this Book would be finiſhed, and ſeeing ſo little notice taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the general, of all the Patience and Long-ſuffering Judgments, and bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs Mercies of the LORD: But all manner of Wickedneſs and open Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>haineſs, appearing openly with an impudent face ſaying, <hi>Who is the LORD <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat we ſhould fear him:</hi> and ſeeing Wickedneſs rage as a peſtilential Fever, and the Angels of darkneſs let looſe out of the Bottomleſs-pit, and Hell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eign on Earth, I thought in my ſelf theſe are the Evil-days wherein the Prudent are to keep ſilence, and the Days of Vengance are at hand: I threw the writing out of my hand, as <hi>Moſes</hi> threw the Tables of Stone, out of his hand, and concluded all in vaine that was ſpent in labour of Love upon this Generation, which is paſſing away like the Smoak of a Furnace; for thought I, the time is come, That he that is wicked muſt be wicked ſtill, and he that is righteous ſhall be righteous.</p>
            <p>But in this Exerciſe of Mind, the power of his Love broke in upon me, who was never weary in Well-doing, and charged me with Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of my Duty that would a-mount to his Glory, and the Good of Souls: Upon this I haſtned again to the Work I had laid a-ſide, and ſince I have grudg'd the time that hath been ſpent from it; and now I have given you an Account why it was not committed to the Preſs before now.</p>
            <p>The next is the Salutation of the Love of God to all, of what Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſoever, whether in Forms, or out of Forms, through out the whole Univerſe that loves no Iniquity; but the Truth as it is in Jeſus, my Soul hath fellowſhip with you herein, and if you preſevere to the end of all Iniquity, to deſtroy the Root and Ground of all Evil, that the Righteous Seed which is Heir of the Kingdom of Glory may be ſown in the good Ground, which will bring forth Fruit to God an Hundred Fold.</p>
            <p>Friends of all Perſwaſions that are in this Work, all the Promiſes are yours, the Bleſſing of the everlaſting Hills is upon your heads, the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God is your Refuge, and under his Arms you ſhall be preſerved for ever, he ſhall caſt out the Enemy before you, and by the Power of his Word deſtroy them; then <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Fountain of <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in ſafety, in a Land of Wheat and Wine; his Heavens ſhall drop the Dew. Bleſſed art thou Oh People ſaved by the LORD, the Sheild of thy help, which is the Sword of thy Glory, therefore thine Enemies ſhall be in ſubjection unto thee, and thou ſhall tread upon their high Places. <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.27, 28, 29. But the Hipocrite, the Proud, the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, the Malicious, the Back-biter, Lier and Slanderer ſhall have their Portion in the Lake; the Self-ended ſhall wither, the Luke-warm, GOD
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36863:20"/>will ſpew out; the Wicked of the World and Sinners in <hi>Sion</hi> God will thruſt a-way, as Thorns that cannot be touched with hands, therefore muſt be burnt up in the place where they ſtand. But unto thoſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fears my Name, ſhall the Sun of Righteouſneſs a-riſe with Healings li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Wings, and they ſhall be mine in the Day that I make up my Jewels and I will ſpare you, as a Man ſpareth his only Son that ſerves him ſaith the LORD.</p>
            <p>As I lay on my Bed waiting upon the LORD, having my ſelf and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worldly things in a low eſteem and value, humbling my ſelf to the duſt and making Self of no Reputation, but having a wonderful great and high eſteem of GOD beyond what my Tongue is able to expreſs, to love adore, and follow him, without the leaſt intereſt of my own, let it be ever ſo holy, ſo it be according to his divine Will: And as I was thus giving my ſelf all up to GOD, a powerful Voice ſaid, <hi>Write down thy Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty,</hi> which I immediately did, and ſaid</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>My LORD, and my GOD, that I may uſe no vain Repetitions to Thee, but that which comes from me to Thee, may be the Begettings of thy own Life. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I beſeech Thee be Thou the Begetter of every Thought that riſes in me to thee, for then ſhall my Prayer be exceptable to Thee when Thou art the Father of it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Then may the LORD of Life and Glory ſay,</hi> This is my Beloved in whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> am well pleaſed: <hi>For LORD what am I but as the Duſt before Thee, who am nothing, nor can do nothing, not ſo much as keep out a wandring Thought, or keep my Mind fixt upon Thee one moment; therefore I lie in my own vileneſs, in my own Corruption, who am nothing, nor can do nothing. No, righteous LORD, without Thee I can do nothing, but in thee holy Father, and by thy Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Power I can do all things, Glory be to Thee. All weakneſs is mine, but all Power, and evenlaſting Strength is thine: Thou Omnipotent GOD, unto whom my Heart and Soul, Strength and Might, Poverty and Nothingneſs, ye, all that is within me doth aſcribe unto Thee the Everlaſting Majeſty, all Honour and Glory, all Love and humble Obedience, with everlaſting Praiſes and Thankſgiving be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned unto Thee, the HOLY ONE,</hi> Amen, <hi>ſaith my Soul, World without End,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>J. W.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And whereas it is thought by ſome that are ſtrangers to me and my Writings, that a Woman did not write theſe Books which I have pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forth, but, at leaſt ſay, that I have the help of ſome Man; give GOD the glory, <hi>Jone Whitrow</hi> writ every Word, I, poor nothing unworthy Creatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wrote it, I cannot ſay whether a Word might be miſpelt and mended but otherways my Hands writ them (and can produce many Witneſſe that ſaw me write them) and I had no help, but the help of the LORD neither hath there been any hand with me, but the hand of the LORD
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36863:21"/>which was ſtrong upon me till I had finiſhed them: And why ſhould it be thought incredible for a Woman to write truth, any more than a Man? Is the Spirit of the LORD ſtraightned, that it cannot operate in a Woman as well as in a Man? Is not he able to open the Mouth of an Aſs? Yes, to reprove the madneſs of the Prophets, that trains the People up in ſuch blindneſs, and groſs Ignorance: Dare you preſume to limmit the Maker of all things, to any thing that had a beginning? Was not his firſt appearance to Women after his Reſurrection, who ſent <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> and the other <hi>Mary,</hi> with the glad Tidings thereof to his Diſciples? And did he not open the heart of <hi>Lidia?</hi> And did not the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>Help thoſe Women that are Fellow-labourers with me in the Goſpel of Chriſt, Philippians</hi> 4.3. And <hi>Deborah</hi> the Propheteſs judged <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and they came to her for Judgment, and ſhe bid <hi>Barak</hi> go to War with <hi>Jabin</hi> the King of <hi>Haſor,</hi> but <hi>Barak,</hi> though a Man, was timerous and fearful, and would not go without <hi>Deborah</hi> went with him, and ſhe ſung Praiſe for the great Deliverance. But the Honour of the Battel was given <hi>Jael,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Hebor, Judges</hi> 4. And did not King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> after he had heard the Law read, rent his Cloths and wept; therefore the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Hilkiah,</hi> the Prieſt, and <hi>Ahikam,</hi> the Son of <hi>Shaphan,</hi> and <hi>Achbor,</hi> the Son of <hi>Michaiah,</hi> and <hi>Shaphan</hi> the Chancellor, and <hi>Afaiah,</hi> the King's ſervant, ſaying, <hi>Go ye and enquire of the LORD for me, and for the People,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>Helkia</hi> the Prieſt, and <hi>Shaphan</hi> the Chancellor, with the reſt of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, went unto <hi>Huldah,</hi> the Propheteſs, the Wife of <hi>Shallum,</hi> who dwelt in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in the College, and they communed with her. 2 <hi>Kings chap.</hi> 22. Hear you may ſee the LORD made uſe of Women, as well as Men, and will make uſe of them yet more; now he is coming to pour out his Spirit upon all Fleſh.<hi>Joel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From one that is in Unity and Fellowſhip with all that fears GOD, and keeps his Commandements throughout the Univerſe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jane Whitrow.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <div type="vision">
               <head>John Hall<hi>'s Viſion upon the firſt Day of the Eleventh Month,</hi> 1692/3.</head>
               <p>AS I went to accompany a publick Friend <hi>John Cooper</hi> to a Meeting, I was, me-thoughts as it were ſpiritually in a Glorious place, where I ſtood before the Lord, where was alſo <hi>William Warin,</hi> who had there received an Errand, and, as it were, vaniſhed out of my ſight on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and was gone to deliver it, but I was left behind: And me-thought I ſaw him that ſent <hi>William,</hi> bring forth a very great golden Trumpet of a large ſize, and deliver'd it unto me, and bid me Proclaim: And im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after to an Angel that ſtood by, he deliver'd a Sword, and bid him ſmite; and me-thoughts the ſound of the Trumpet cauſed ſuch an
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36863:21"/>Allarm, that it awakened the very-Dead, and as the Sound waxed lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and louder, and the Cry great. I thought I ſaw Hipocrites and Back-ſliders, the ſinners in <hi>Sion,</hi> hang down their Heads, nay, and after ſometime quit the room, as not being able to abide it, the Power of the LORD did wonderfully break in: And this, by the Command of the LORD, I commit to Writing, as a Teſtimony for him, which the LORD in his own due time will bring to paſs. Written at my Habitation at <hi>Monkhelſden,</hi> by a Servant of the Lord, whoſe outward Name is</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>The</hi> 
                     <date>27th <hi>of the</hi> 1ſt. <hi>Month.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>John Hall.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="vision">
               <p>Upon the 22d. of the laſt Month, being the 12th. Month, my Siſter <hi>Grace Hall</hi> being at a Meeting at <hi>Raly</hi> with <hi>Jane Vickers,</hi> the Word of the LORD came unto her ſaying, <hi>Write,</hi> and continued as an Exerciſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her: On the Night her Sleep went from her, after ſhe aroſe ſhe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew into a Chamber, and the following Words, word by word were given her, ſhe not knowing the next Word as ſhe writ, whereof ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently gave me an Account.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Thus ſaith the LORD,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I Have a great Work to do in the Earth, and terrible ſhall it be to the Wicked; but ſay unto mine Elect on this wiſe: Ye ſhall be kept in ſafety if ye obey my Word, I will be with the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous whereſoever they are, if they will but ſeparate the Wicked from among them; but if they will not put away the Wicked from among them, then ſhall my Hand be heavier upon the Righteous for the Wicked's ſake: And ſay unto the Wicked on this manner, There is yet a little ſpace for you, if ye will repent of your Wickedneſs, and Turn unto me, ſaith the Lord: You may read how it was in the Days of Old, it ſhall be no leſs in this the Day of my Wrath, ſaith the Lord; for though</hi> Noah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel <hi>and</hi> Job <hi>were righteous, and although there be ſome ſuch non-a-days, yet they ſhall ſave nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Son nor Daughter; they ſhall ſave only their own Souls.</hi> Written by <hi>Grace Hall,</hi> being 16 Years, 3 Months, and 8 Days old.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter to a Friend from Jamaca, Spaniſh-Town the 19th of <hi>June.</hi> 1692.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Loving Brother,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>This is to give thee a true and ſatisfactory Account of our Misfortune: There hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on the 7th Inſtant, about half an hour after 11 at Noon, a terrible Earth-quake thoughout the whole Iſland of <hi>Jamaca,</hi> it hath not left a Houſe ſtanding in the whole place, that was built of either Stone, or Brick, nor any thing that was built with the ſame Meterials, but what it hath made inſufficient, for tho' ſome of theſe ſtand, they are not fit to live in, neither dare we hardly come near them, becauſe of the frequent ſhakes we ſtill have: All thoſe that it hath pleaſed the Almighty to ſave in giving them their Lives for a Prey, do now think a <hi>Negro</hi>'s houſe that is walled and daubed wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Morter, and Thatched, the Eves hanging down almoſt to the ground, a pleaſant Houſe. Hear you may ſee Colonels, and great Men, bowing their Bodies to creep into this little Hutch; who before had Houſes fit not only to receive, but to feaſt in an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner, a Prince or King, as great as <hi>England</hi>'s Monarch upon ocaſion, and now by this ſad Diſaſter have hardly Bread to eat, and never a Houſe to be in.</p>
               <p>The Ground opened at <hi>Port Royal,</hi> where I dwell, with a ſhake, and ſwallowed whole Houſes, nay, the Street I dwell in was in leſs than 3 Hours after, 4 Fathom under Water, and nothing of my Houſe to be ſeen, nor any other, only one Timber-houſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36863:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>which <hi>George Philips</hi> lived in. The ſhake opened the Earth, the Water flew up, and carried the People in quick: I loſt my Wife, my Son, a Prentice, a white Maid, and 6 Slaves, and all that ever I had in the World; my Land where I was ready to raiſe five Houſes, and had room to raiſe ten more, is all ſunk, a good Sloop may ſail over it, as well as over the Point: I have not ſaved a Rag, nor any Money, but I find people kind where I never thought they would; all that it pleaſed God to ſave was my own life, my Daughter <hi>Mary,</hi> and 8 good Slaves, but I have nothing to give them to eat. Captain <hi>Gomings</hi> and Captain <hi>Martin</hi> are both ſwallowed up, and <hi>Georg. Philips</hi> periſhed; his Wife comes over in the <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ah Brother! If thou didſt ſee thoſe great Perſons that are now dead upon the Water, thou couldſt never forget it: Great Men, who were ſo ſwallowed up with Pride, that a Man could not be admitted to ſpeak with them, and Women whoſe Top-knots ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to reach the Clouds, now lie ſtinking upon the Water, and are made Meat for Fiſh, and Fowls of the Air: My heart is full, yet I cannot forget the Mercy of God to me, and many others.</p>
               <closer>I reſt
<signed>thy Loving Brother <hi>John Pike.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Part of a Letter to a Friend.</head>
               <p>AND concerning <hi>John Hall</hi>'s Meſſage, I think it may be of as great Service, as any thing I know, for let it be ſo as you ſay, and believe that it was a Myſtery, and concerns that People he was ſent to deliver it to, which, for ought I know, may very well be. My reaſon is, becauſe he was ſent to them, and to none elſe beſides them, yet that will not quit the general, for it was revealed to me in a Viſion in King <hi>Jame's</hi> Reign, when his Camp was preparing for <hi>Hounſlow-heath;</hi> the Deſtruction of <hi>London,</hi> but the time was never yet ſhew'd me, therefore who knows, it may be the City of <hi>London,</hi> as well as the City of Profeſſion, whoſe fair Fabrick ſhall be laid low; and tho' his Meſſage was to that particular People, of Ruin and Deſtruction, my Meſſage is to all thro' the Univerſe, where the Iniquity is found; and for certain I ſay again and again, in the Word of the LORD, That the LORD GOD Omnipotent is riſen, the Everlaſting God is riſen to plead with all Fleſh: For this was the Word of the Lord to me, <hi>I will ſift the Nations as in Ceive, and winow them as Wheat is winowed for the Mill.</hi> And again, ſaid the LORD, <hi>Children ſhall loſe their Fundamental Laws.</hi> Again, <hi>Though</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Samuel <hi>ſtood before me, yet ſhall they not Diſannul what I have Decreed.</hi> But why do you think that <hi>London</hi> ſhould ſcape the Judgments of God any more than <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Jamaca?</hi> Your Anſwer may be, Becauſe of the Righteous that are in it: Do you think there was not one <hi>Malines</hi> in <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia,</hi> nor one Righteous-ſoul in all <hi>Jamaica,</hi> where the Earth open'd and ſwallowed up their Bodies, but their Heads left above-ground, which the Dogs eat? Yes, I am ſure there was; and there was one in the old World, and yet it was deſtroyed, but the LORD knows how to deliver his <hi>Noah's,</hi> by getting them into the Ark of his Power, and to ſave his juſt <hi>Lots,</hi> by flying out of <hi>Sodom;</hi> his choſen Ones that cries Day and Night unto him, that no Iniquity may be found in them, but that they may be ſanctified throughout in Body, Soul and Spirit, that they may be wiſe Virgins that hath Oil in their Lamps, and their Lights burning, that when the Mid-night-cry comes, they may be ready to go in with their LORD into the Marriage-Chamber. But what think you of thoſe high-flown Profeſſors of our Times, that makes ſuch a bluſtring-noiſe about Religion, ſome in Forms, and ſome out? That have their Hundreds and Thouſands, and yet let their Fellow-creatures want Bread, in and about the City of <hi>London:</hi> Do you think ſuch do not highly provoke the LORD to take away their Hundreds and Thouſands from them, or them from their Treaſures, or both periſh together, by ſome ſignal and amazing Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? As he did in <hi>Jamaca,</hi> and other places, who, <hi>Judas</hi> like, grudges what is ſpent upon the LORD in any kind whatſoever.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
